<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Metellus his dialogues the first part, containing a relation of a journey to Tunbridge-Wells : also a description of the Wells and place : with the fourth book of Virgil's Æneids in English / written under that name, by a gentleman of this nation, sometime gentleman commoner of Christ-Church in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Lewkenor, John, 1657 or 8-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10938</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13568388</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13568388</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100354</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100354)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 462:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Metellus his dialogues the first part, containing a relation of a journey to Tunbridge-Wells : also a description of the Wells and place : with the fourth book of Virgil's Æneids in English / written under that name, by a gentleman of this nation, sometime gentleman commoner of Christ-Church in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Lewkenor, John, 1657 or 8-1706.</author>
                  <author>Virgil. Aeneis. Liber 4. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 131 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Warren, for N. Rolls ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Metellus is the pseudonym of John Lewkenor.  Cf. B.M.</note>
                  <note>No other parts of "Metellus his dialogues" found.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100354:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100354:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>METELLUS</hi> HIS DIALOGUES. The Firſt PART, Containing a RELATION OF A JOURNEY TO <hi>Tunbridge-Wells;</hi> Alſo a <hi>Deſcription</hi> of the <hi>WELLS</hi> and <hi>PLACE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the Fourth BOOK of <hi>Virgil</hi>'s <hi>AENEIDS</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written under that Name, by a Gentleman of this Nation, ſometime Gentleman Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Warren,</hi> for <hi>N. Rolls</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100354:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100354:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable WILLIAM LORD <hi>BIRON,</hi> BARON of <hi>RATCHDELL.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Orphan Book, that can by no modiſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours recommend it ſelf to the pleaſant Men of the Time, nor by Satyrizing <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> can hope to have a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on its ſide; muſt needs be aſſured of many Adverſaries, and can be in hope but of very few Friends. It flies, My Lord, therefore firſt (to almoſt all
<pb facs="tcp:100354:3"/>that is left of 'em) the Shadow and Name of the Ancient He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes; begs an Adoption to the vertuous Name, and asks leave to make uſe of the Voice of <hi>Metellus:</hi> not daring, under a leſs Capacity, to ſpeak to the Vices of our Age. It hears, my Lord, from the Ghoſt of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Curio,</hi> which here it has rais'd,
<q>Livor edax tibi cuncta negat,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc. Pharſ.</hi> lib. 1.</note>
               </q> which though he ſpake only to <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his life-time, his Ghoſt may yet, with truth enough, remember leſs Men of it now: At a time when Party, when Picque, when Paſſion, when In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, when but fanſied Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may every thing, to any Man, deny.</p>
            <p>Therefore this Orphan, to decline the ſtroak of ſo wild a
<pb facs="tcp:100354:3"/>Paſſion, as Envy has always appeared to the literate World, falls to the ground, as expert Hunters often do, before the ſavage wild Boar: and far,
<note place="margin">When it turns upon 'em.</note> from the Ambition of conteſting with ſuch an Adverſary as the beſt ſcarce withſtand, vaniſheth from the ſight of the World: Leaves the Ghoſt of great <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellus,</hi> the Light of Reaſon, and the Voice of impregnable Truth, in the mouths of ſharp <hi>Acer,</hi> and eloquent <hi>Curio,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute Libertinage with the Age: eſpecially in the Second, and Third Part, where, grown to more Virility, it attacks the pregnant Vices of the Time, and adventures to combat with the Darling of our Days. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from ſuch mouths as thoſe, to ſpeak inoffenſively Truth; if not to the Perſons (which this
<pb facs="tcp:100354:4"/>Book altogether declines) at leaſt, to the Vices of the Times.</p>
            <p>By this happy neceſſity, this Little Book, dignified, my Lord, and adopted to the vertuous Name of <hi>Metellus,</hi> now truly ennobled, addreſſes to your Lordſhip (not as ſuch Orphans and Deſtitutes commonly do) preſuming upon the Nearneſs of Blood its Authour has to your Lordſhip, and that Noble Family of your Name; but by a higher impulſe of Nature, yet (as Iron to the Load-ſtone goes) by a natural Sympathy the brave <hi>BIRONS</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> have, with the vertuous and glorious <hi>Metelli</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> this Little Book, by <hi>Metellus</hi> adopted, to your Lordſhip now naturally comes; and hopes, that for the <hi>Palladium</hi>'s ſake, by its brave adopting Anceſtour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued
<pb facs="tcp:100354:4"/>from the burning Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<note place="margin">Of <hi>Veſta.</hi>
               </note> it may find Favour and Countenance, from a Family, who have been as great Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of <hi>Minerva,</hi> as Servants of <hi>Mars;</hi> and who are (beyond all Alliance of Blood) to the glorious <hi>Metellus,</hi> in Bravery, of Kin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Metellus</hi> reſcu'd from flames the <hi>Palladium</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> The <hi>BIRONS,</hi> had not Fate it ſelf been a Foe, and had not our Sins been our Enemies too, had reſcued from the worſt of Confuſions more than the <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladium</hi> here.
<note place="margin">Non habet ſcientia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimicum praeter igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiam.</note> Not only our U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities from Ignorance, the only Enemy Science has in the World; our Churches from Profanation and Sacriledge; our Monarch, and Monarchy it ſelf, from Aſſaſſination; our Countrey from Slavery worſe
<pb facs="tcp:100354:5"/>than thoſe flames: if all had been as brave as faithful, and of as good Lives as they. Men, if not the moſt admired, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the moſt deſerving Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any of their time. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven brave Brothers, ſix of them Knighted for their Bravery and Birth.
<note place="margin">
                  <p>My Lord <hi>John Biron,</hi> the Eldeſt Brother, General.</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Newark,</hi> which he bravely defended.</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> ſometime General of the Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of the then Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> his own Regiment of Horſe, ſlain in the War. Sir <hi>William,</hi> and the other Two Field-Officers, one of 'em ſlain at <hi>York</hi> in Defence of the Town.</p>
               </note> The Eldeſt deſervedly honoured with a Barony, which he bought with his Blood. All in eminent Command, all emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſuffering, all eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acting for their Country and King; might juſtly be thought, (as one well obſerv'd of 'em) the braveſt ſeven Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have appeared in the World ſince the <hi>Maccabees</hi> days. A Family deſerving Eternal Memory, if it were but for the brave Actions of the Eldeſt,
<pb facs="tcp:100354:5"/>the then victorious Head of that Family, that had ſo much Heart, my Lord <hi>JOHN BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RON;</hi> who, to ſay nothing of thoſe ſo many perſonal Brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his, as that at <hi>Brill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>In <hi>Oxford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In <hi>Wilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and elſewhere: At <hi>Round-way-down,</hi> with Fifteen hundred Horſe and Dragoons, he not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, but abſolutely routed a conſiderable Army of Horſe and Foot, under no unskilful General; where he took Two and forty Colours, all their Cannon, all their Baggage, and almoſt as many Priſoners as he had Men: more might be remembred, but
<q>Satis eſt hanc mihi noſſe manum.
<note place="margin">Mart. Epig. de Scaev.</note>
               </q> Yet to theſe brave ſeven Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we muſt add the brave Uncle, Sir <hi>NICHOLAS BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RON,</hi> Governour of <hi>Weſt-Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:100354:6"/>one of the Generals of the Royal Army, and one of our then greateſt Maſters of the Military Art, your Lordſhip's great Uncle; the Eighth good, the Eighth brave Man, of the ſame Family, and the ſame Name, at the ſame time ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and with hazard of all they had, fighting for their Country, and defending their King.</p>
            <p>Pardon therefore, My Lord, if this little Orphan, adopted by the great <hi>Metellus,</hi> from its Cradle as it were, preſume to Addreſs it ſelf to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the immediate Heir, and Sncceſſour, of ſo great a Name as <hi>BIRON</hi> is here; ſince in you, as in your Noble Anceſtours, Bravery ſtill, and Ingenuity join; Qualities that ſympathize ſo much with the Name of <hi>Metell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:100354:6"/>In this Firſt Part, My Lord, as in its younger Years, it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends but to divertiſe your Lordſhip with a pleaſant Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude to a more ſerious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; but in the Second and Third Part, grown to more Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rility, it will entertain your Nobler, and more Heroick Thoughts. Its Authour being Ambitious but to be Eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's Moſt faithful humble Servant, and affectionate Kinſman, <hi>J. L.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:100354:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100354:7"/>
            <head>A CHARACTER OF THE PERSONS Who ſpeak in theſe DIALOGUES.</head>
            <list>
               <item>METELL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, A Lover of VERT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E, and eminently Learned.</item>
               <item>ACER, A Divine, of a ſharp Wit, and eloquent.</item>
               <item>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIO, A Civilian, and an eloquent Man.</item>
               <item>AESC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LAPE, A Learned Phyſician, and good Companion; but inclined to <hi>Epicurus</hi> his Opinions.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:100354:8"/>LAELI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, A witty young Gentleman, but a Deiſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Or take their</hi> Characters <hi>thus:</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Deſerving of that Name, the great <hi>Metell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In Vertue and in Learning does excell.</l>
               <l>Eloquent <hi>Curio</hi> pleads, and does commend.</l>
               <l>Sharp <hi>Acer</hi> does both teach and reprehend.</l>
               <l>Learn'd <hi>Aeſculape</hi> by Reaſon's Light can ſee</l>
               <l>In Nature far; ſcarce to Divinity.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laelius</hi> declares th' Opinions of the Times;</l>
               <l>Too honeſt to be guilty of the Crimes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100354:8"/>
            <head>THE Firſt Dialogue.</head>
            <head type="sub">A JOURNEY TO <hi>Tunbridge-Wells.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Metellus.</speaker>
               <l>THE Sun was now come to his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney's end</l>
               <l>For that half year, beginning to deſcend,</l>
               <l>When me and <hi>Laelius,</hi> who had both been ill,</l>
               <l>And long had lingred under th' Artiſt skill:</l>
               <l>A learn'd Phyſician, knowing none cou'd mend</l>
               <l>Like thoſe that made; did prudently pretend</l>
               <l>To cure by Nature; or as Nature cou'd,</l>
               <l>Did we apply t' her; ſo this Doctor wou'd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100354:9"/>Sometimes by wiſe Digreſſion from the Arts,</l>
               <l>Cure Men by ſending 'em to wholeſome parts</l>
               <l>Of the Great World, with which the Leſs muſt be;</l>
               <l>If they'll be well, ſtill in good harmony.</l>
               <l>God-like he firſt ordained us the ſcent</l>
               <l>Of Fragrant <hi>Earth;</hi> and then as if he'd meant</l>
               <l>To give us at each Doſe an Element,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Air</hi> this <hi>Aeſculape</hi> to quicken gave,</l>
               <l>Waters to cleanſe us; if thoſe cou'd not ſave,</l>
               <l>Then Nature-like too he ordain'd the Grave.</l>
               <l>Deſtructive Fire this <hi>Aeſculape</hi> did uſe,</l>
               <l>But not in Element, and crude, t' abuſe</l>
               <l>Too tender Man: but dulcify'd by Vine,</l>
               <l>Great Nature's Limbeck, and deſtill'd to Wine;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>"Good Wine the greateſt chearer of the heart,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>"The Natural Reſtorative of Art.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wine from the Teats of Nature, and not Brew'd,</l>
               <l>He allow'd himſelf and us for Laſſitude.</l>
               <l>And this was his fourth Doſe, which Nature meant,</l>
               <l>As he taught well, for a fifth Element:</l>
               <l>Wine firſt by Nature thus, for Stomach's ſake,</l>
               <l>Then giv'n by <hi>Paul,</hi> we like <hi>Ambroſta</hi> take,</l>
               <l>With Terrene God, our <hi>Aeſculape,</hi> to whom</l>
               <l>We offer 'of healthy Cups a <hi>Hecatomb.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100354:9"/>That doleful night, before we went away;</l>
               <l>In that took leave, ſo dy'd till the third day;</l>
               <l>Not like old <hi>Trojans,</hi> buried lay in Wine,</l>
               <l>But like true <hi>Trojans</hi> till we meet repine.</l>
               <l>Not buried at all; for not at reſt;</l>
               <l>Nor did we paſs that time among the bleſt;</l>
               <l>But like Men damn'd from Paradiſe, in pain</l>
               <l>And labour live, till we our bliſs regain:</l>
               <l>Till all at <hi>Tunbridge-Wells</hi> again alive</l>
               <l>Meet, and each other kindly do revive,</l>
               <l>With Water, and good Air, and blood of Grape,</l>
               <l>Good Company and divine <hi>Aeſculape.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We were five Scholars; four went two and two,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curio</hi> and I, who had no more to do</l>
               <l>But to take Air, and then to take our eaſe;</l>
               <l>And nought elſe being preſcrib'd for our Diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Together rid; that hard by the mid-way,</l>
               <l>We might with Liquor quench the ſcorching day,</l>
               <l>Early before the Exc'llent Doctor went</l>
               <l>On Horſeback, with accompliſht Patient,</l>
               <l>Honeſteſt <hi>Laelius,</hi> who of Wit had ſtore,</l>
               <l>But of wiſe Patience had a great deal more.</l>
               <l>And doubtleſs 'twas the fortunateſt hit,</l>
               <l>"That one had Patience, when they both had Wit.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100354:10"/>He talking, taught; t' other well pleas'd to learn;</l>
               <l>They each; each others Excellence diſcern.</l>
               <l>As Nature's Active, and her Paſſive do,</l>
               <l>So do theſe well pair'd Naturaliſts too</l>
               <l>Agree, concurr in all things, jump and hit;</l>
               <l>Happy 'n ſo great a Sympathy of Wit.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acer,</hi> to whom <hi>Minerva</hi> ſtill was kind,</l>
               <l>Yet Fortune frown'd on; he was left behind,</l>
               <l>Whether unwilling to ride that long way,</l>
               <l>As his good Friends did, through in one hot day,</l>
               <l>Or froward Fortune (long by him deſpis'd)</l>
               <l>Goddeſs, to whom he never ſacriſic'd,</l>
               <l>Had damn'd him for a day into the Jaws</l>
               <l>Of modern Furies, and the modiſh Claws</l>
               <l>Of Harpies of this Age, we do not know;</l>
               <l>But he in Stage-Coach is condemn'd to go</l>
               <l>Without his Friends —</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curio</hi> and I were ſomething better bleſt;</l>
               <l>Riding before, eſcap'd that Harpy's Neſt.</l>
               <l>All different ways with different Fate we went,</l>
               <l>In hopes of different Divertiſement:</l>
               <l>Yet at the <hi>Wells</hi> with <hi>Acer</hi> we arriv'd,</l>
               <l>There, <hi>Aeſculape,</hi> who had been well reviv'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100354:10"/>Not with cold Waters, but with more divine,</l>
               <l>More animating Liquor, <hi>Gaſcoigne</hi> Wine,</l>
               <l>Hard by the <hi>Wells</hi> ſtood, with his Learned Mate,</l>
               <l>Like old <hi>Anchiſe,</hi> contemplating our Fate,</l>
               <l>Father of Wits.—</l>
               <l>When we on Horſeback, <hi>Acer,</hi> in a Coach</l>
               <l>With ſome odd kind of Damſells, did approach,</l>
               <l>They ſtop, ſtep out; When "Oh! What haſt thou done,</l>
               <l>"Baſe Fortune, with <hi>Minerva</hi>'s Minion?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laelius</hi> cry'd out. "None of <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Race,</l>
               <l>"None of the Nine theſe are! What God cou'd place</l>
               <l>"Thus Ingenuity? Muſt Fate be Foe,</l>
               <l>"Spightful to all that <hi>Pallas</hi> favours ſo?</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Aeſculape</hi> drew near; And art thou come</l>
               <l>At laſt, dear Friend, to our <hi>Elyſium?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How 'fraid were we? kindly then we embrace,</l>
               <l>Welcome each other to the pleaſant place.</l>
               <l>Our next Care was to ſeek a Houſe, where we,</l>
               <l>For one Month's time, might all of us be free</l>
               <l>From that <hi>worſt Plague of Wit, Ill-Company.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We wander on; ſome pretty Houſes ſee,</l>
               <l>Which in that place (though wild enough) there be.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100354:11"/>The Doctor pleas'd himſelf: his airy Friend,</l>
               <l>Who more did to good Company pretend,</l>
               <l>Than Bookiſh ſolitude, an airy place</l>
               <l>Soon found, which airy Company did grace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acer</hi> and <hi>Curio</hi> ſought no happineſs</l>
               <l>But Solitude, the likelieſt place to bleſs,</l>
               <l>We thought, the Deſart of that Wilderneſs.</l>
               <l>We wander all a pretty while before</l>
               <l>We ſee a Cottage: Cottage, and no more</l>
               <l>At laſt we find; A ſweet and pleaſant place,</l>
               <l>A ſituation that had Nature's Face;</l>
               <l>That lookt like the firſt Times, that ſeem'd to be</l>
               <l>Some Patrimony of poor Honeſty;</l>
               <l>The greeneſt Plat that was in all that wild</l>
               <l>And ſpacious Heath, and the moſt undefil'd:</l>
               <l>Nor Luſt nor Envy cou'd have Object there,</l>
               <l>Pride was a bulk too big for it to bear.</l>
               <l>Seat for Chriſtianity: were Chriſt but near,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> might wiſh a Tabernacle here.</l>
               <l>This is the Deſart then, ſaid <hi>Acer,</hi> we</l>
               <l>In ſuch a Cottage, <hi>Curio,</hi> may be free.</l>
               <l>The wiſh'd for Tabernacle, which we crave,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elias</hi> ſolitude, we here may have.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100354:11"/>And to aſſure that Pleaſure too, we ſee,</l>
               <l>Said <hi>Curio,</hi> here St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Poverty.</l>
               <l>Green cloſe behind it, and ſweet Springs were nigh,</l>
               <l>On th' one ſide Wood, and the green Corn hard by:</l>
               <l>The Front lay open to the ample Heath:</l>
               <l>Which from all Quarters ſent a purer Breath</l>
               <l>Than Towns enjoy.</l>
               <l>Beſet with Fern and Shrubs: Shrubs were as high</l>
               <l>As th' humble Cottage: Taller Trees were nigh;</l>
               <l>A Houſe ſecur'd by being poor and low;</l>
               <l>"<hi>O happy thoſe who live ſecured ſo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Where no fierce Winds of Pride and Envy blow!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Before the Door ſtood an old Aſh that made</l>
               <l>By Nature, pleaſant and convenient Shade.</l>
               <l>Of which the Owner had contriv'd a Bower,</l>
               <l>Enough to ſave poor Man from Sun or Shower;</l>
               <l>But place, which Nature ſurely had deſign'd</l>
               <l>For higher things, for ſhelter to the Mind.</l>
               <l>For we, ſoon as we ſaw it, thought it fit</l>
               <l>In ſuch a Solitude to ſhelter Wit.</l>
               <l>Here an old Dame came cleanly to the Door</l>
               <l>'Soon as we knock'd, came cleanly, and no more,</l>
               <l>But holding the ſmall Door half-open, ſaid,</l>
               <l>"'Las! Sirs, 'tis late, and we're all going to bed.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100354:12"/>"We ſee no Gallants here, nor entertain</l>
               <l>"Such Men as you; we ſcarce think't worth our pain;</l>
               <l>"Nor have I Linen clean, nor can I give</l>
               <l>"You dainty Meats; on hardeſt Fare we live.</l>
               <l>And then ſhe told us what ill luck ſhe'd had,</l>
               <l>Not long ago, with Strangers as well clad:</l>
               <l>Nor truly cou'd ſhe, and ſo near to Night,</l>
               <l>Receive Men ſo unknown, at the firſt ſight.</l>
               <l>But no ſuch Men, reply'd our Learned Friend,</l>
               <l>Theſe honeſt Gallants are; the only End</l>
               <l>That brings them hither, is but to retreat,</l>
               <l>They for their quiet ſeek this Rural Seat.</l>
               <l>But if with you theſe Verbal Motives fail,</l>
               <l>This at leaſt will (and ſhew'd ſome Gold) prevail.</l>
               <l>"<hi>O what won't Woman for thee, Gold, forſake?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>For thee, Gold, what won't Woman undertake?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The good Dame had not for ſome time before</l>
               <l>Seen ſuch a ſight, ſcarce hop'd to ſee it more:</l>
               <l>Fixing her Eyes upon the Golden Gift,</l>
               <l>"Well, ſaid ſhe then, come in, we'll make a ſhift.</l>
               <l>Non quiet then ſhe ſought, nor trouble fear'd,</l>
               <l>When the old Gold of <hi>Aeſculape</hi> appear'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100354:12"/>We enter, and the old <hi>Sylveſtrian</hi> Dame</l>
               <l>O'er lofty Threſholds follow, till we came</l>
               <l>To that part of the Hovel, they call Hall,</l>
               <l>Where ſhe with Rural Majeſty did call</l>
               <l>Her Daughter firſt, and then her brawny Son,</l>
               <l>And then the Maid: and when all that was done,</l>
               <l>Oft going to and fro, at laſt ſhe brought</l>
               <l>A piece of Pye, of Hare, her Son had caught,</l>
               <l>With fatter Mutton bak'd, which ſhe had bought.</l>
               <l>She pray'd us to ſit down, nor did we ſpare,</l>
               <l>But all each other invite to the cold Fare.</l>
               <l>We ſup, whilſt the whole Family attends:</l>
               <l>They wait like Servants, and they look like Friends.</l>
               <l>Th'old Woman, and her Son, her Maid, his Wife,</l>
               <l>The honeſt Conſorts of that homely Life.</l>
               <l>At laſt, to make amends for the cold Cheer,</l>
               <l>Th'old Woman bids bring forth laſt <hi>Eaſter</hi>'s Beer.</l>
               <l>The Maid and Daughter draw: the Maple Cup</l>
               <l>They briskly ſill: we briskly drink it up.</l>
               <l>All welcome us to all, as they may ſay,</l>
               <l>Free of their Ale, as willingly we ſtay.</l>
               <l>When we had ſupp'd, we all began to caſt</l>
               <l>Our Eyes on <hi>Acer;</hi> wou'd he not at laſt</l>
               <l>Relate his Journey? tell us what had paſt?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100354:13"/>Nothing cou'd be to us, and over Ale,</l>
               <l>In ſuch a Houſe, more ſeaſonable Tale.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acer.</speaker>
               <l>But he reply'd, "O Friends forbear to ask</l>
               <l>"So hard a thing; It is no pleaſant task</l>
               <l>"For a tir'd Poet, twelve long hours immur'd,</l>
               <l>"In ſuch a Coach, to tell you what h'endur'd.</l>
               <l>"Some things indeed hereafter, but ſcarce theſe</l>
               <l>"Can be ſo well remembred, as to pleaſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lael.</speaker>
               <l>Then, <hi>Laelius</hi> ſpoke. "The Oxe when tir'd ſtrikes ſtrong,</l>
               <l>"Makes ſurer ſteps: 'Tis now 'bove all we long,</l>
               <l>If any ill accident have tir'd thy Wit,</l>
               <l>To hear thy Satyr, here avenging it</l>
               <l>With flaming Fancy, and a well-whet Pen;</l>
               <l>That Fire and Sword of all Ingenious Men.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acer.</speaker>
               <l>"And can my Friends thus importune? muſt I</l>
               <l>"To pleaſe, reiterate a Miſery?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>Said <hi>Acer,</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>"<hi>Lethe,</hi> rather let me ſup</l>
               <l>"Of thy forgetful Streams; fill up my cup,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100354:13"/>"Since to the Pains Fate ſent me, ſure as well</l>
               <l>"I may pretend to th'
<note n="*" place="bottom">To drink of <hi>Lethe</hi> may be ſaid the Courteſie of Hell, becauſe it makes 'em forget all pains.</note> Courteſie of Hell.</l>
               <l>"And as great Reaſon to be waſh'd have I</l>
               <l>"As any of <hi>Anchiſe</hi>'s Progeny.</l>
               <l>"When I to this Etherial Life return,</l>
               <l>"From that Death of bad Company; that Urn</l>
               <l>"Of foetid Coach; ere I from Crew ſo curſt</l>
               <l>"Tranſmigrate well, I muſt drink <hi>Lethe</hi> firſt.</l>
               <l>"Nor Wind, nor Water, nor the ſoaking Rain,</l>
               <l>"Nor <hi>Tunbridge-Wells</hi> can cleanſe from ſuch a ſtain;</l>
               <l>"Of ſuch a Company, of ſuch a Coach,</l>
               <l>"Nothing but <hi>Lethe</hi> waſhes the Reproach.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeſculape</hi> ſmiling then. "In Verſe relate,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Acer,</hi> ſaid he, Satyr will expiate.</l>
               <l>"Slay me thoſe Vultures, which but now we ſaw;</l>
               <l>"Some Portraict of thoſe Dames thou'ſt brought us, draw.</l>
               <l>"Let 'em to <hi>Phoebus</hi> fall; ere they devour</l>
               <l>"Our Livers here, fall by <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Pow'r.</l>
               <l>"The God of Wiſdom cannot chuſe but prize</l>
               <l>"Such Harpy-Vulture Dames in Sacrifice.</l>
               <l>"And thus beſides thou wilt <hi>Minerva</hi> pleaſe,</l>
               <l>"Thus all th' Infernal Furies thou'lt appeaſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100354:14"/>"They'll go for Dainties, when thou'ſt giv'n the blow,</l>
               <l>"Pickled in <hi>Satyr</hi> to the Gods below;</l>
               <l>"Infernal Bitt. Tell then, for God's ſake, tell,</l>
               <l>"How and which way you came? I came from Hell,</l>
               <l>"As once the pious <hi>Trojan</hi> did, ſaid he,</l>
               <l>"To this <hi>Elyſium</hi> of good Company.</l>
               <l>And when he ſaw we all attentive ſate,</l>
               <l>He drew us thus the Landskip of his Fate.</l>
               <l>After that Night, great <hi>Aeſculape,</hi> when we</l>
               <l>Parted ſo late, ſo dolefully from thee,</l>
               <l>Light roſe, but broke not forth; 'twas gloomy Morn,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſeem'd to look at me with ſcorn;</l>
               <l>As if he'd turn'd his back: I ſeem'd to ſee,</l>
               <l>He did not mean to ſhine that day on me.</l>
               <l>Whilſt I, contemplating the Omen, ſate,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curio</hi> rides up, interprets me my Fate.</l>
               <l>Before my Window, on a raw-bon'd Steed</l>
               <l>Sitting, he ſaid, fierce in his Riding-weed:</l>
               <l>Lazieſt of Men, thou art forſaken quite,</l>
               <l>Thoul't bitterly repent it before Night.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100354:14"/>You'll meet with Company, I hope, anon,</l>
               <l>Will make you wiſh, you'd been more early Man.</l>
               <l>Spurring his Horſe, then preſently he fled,</l>
               <l>And left me with <hi>Prediction</hi> murthered.</l>
               <l>"<hi>For the worſt way the Heavens have to kill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Beſides the ſtroke, is to predict the ill.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I, of thee, <hi>Aeſculape,</hi> and theſe bereft,</l>
               <l>Not to too hard, but too ſoft Fate was left</l>
               <l>Of Stage-Coach-Company, and Goſſips prate,</l>
               <l>And one thing more which ten times more I hate,</l>
               <l>Not of that leſſer Curſe of being alone,</l>
               <l>But of a worſe, Damnation, being one</l>
               <l>Man 'mongſt three Women; not the only Man</l>
               <l>That three ſuch Errant Dames hop'd to trepan:</l>
               <l>But th'only that was to be damn'd that day,</l>
               <l>For thirty ſix Miles, to ſuch Birds of Prey.</l>
               <l>Unhappy far, <hi>Prometheus,</hi> beyond thee,</l>
               <l>Who but one Vulture had'ſt, for I had three.</l>
               <l>I often chang'd my Mind, was loth to go;</l>
               <l>Fate at laſt dragg'd me whe'er I wou'd or no.</l>
               <l>The Coach appear'd, and Company I find,</l>
               <l>All Women, but not of the Muſes kind.</l>
               <l>A Northern Lady, Madam <hi>God knows who,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bonny and blith: Her brisk Companion too,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100354:15"/>With a ſtale Maid. What cou'd one Gallant do</l>
               <l>With three ſuch Miſtreſſes, who all wou'd wooe?</l>
               <l>None cou'd be woo'd: Amaz'd awhile I ſtand,</l>
               <l>O Fortune, here, expect thy helping hand:</l>
               <l>Give ſome good Omen, Goddeſs, now I ſaid,</l>
               <l>Treble <hi>Virago</hi> well one Man may dread.</l>
               <l>The Proverb means ſure, two ſuch Dames as theſe,</l>
               <l>That ſays, Two are too much for <hi>Hercules.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For of meer Men, not Two of them, nor Three,</l>
               <l>A Match for the God <hi>Hercules</hi> wou'd be,</l>
               <l>'Leſs Woman too come in; by help of Dame</l>
               <l>We know the dying
<note n="*" place="bottom">Whom <hi>Hercules</hi> ſlew. He to revenge himſelf upon <hi>Hercules,</hi> gave <hi>Deianira</hi> a Coat to ſend him dipp'd in his Blood, which made him fall mad. <hi>Vid. Ovid. Met.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Centaure</hi> overcame.</l>
               <l>He'd need be <hi>Trojan</hi> Hero at the leaſt,</l>
               <l>That but encounters ſuch a Harpy's Neſt;</l>
               <l>But muſt be more that 'ſcapes, or can ſubdue</l>
               <l>That foul beſpattering foeminean Crew,</l>
               <l>That, glorious <hi>Caeſar,</hi> 'd be too much for you.</l>
               <l>I, like <hi>Anchiſes,</hi> then began to pray</l>
               <l>Againſt <hi>Celeno,</hi> 'and Harpyes of the day:</l>
               <l>To any God, if ſacrifice I may,</l>
               <l>I offer Silence, or behind to ſtay.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100354:15"/>Beſeech then Fortune, that ſince ſhe does make</l>
               <l>The Fool oft happy, and the Coxcomb take;</l>
               <l>She'd now do greater work, make Scholar be</l>
               <l>Grateful to Ignorance; to Quean, Honeſty.</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Caeſar</hi> then o'er <hi>Rubicon</hi> I go,</l>
               <l>And Fortune leading, but yet ſtartling too,</l>
               <l>On ſome ſmall Rules of Modeſty I tread,</l>
               <l>Not on all Laws, as 'twas of <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaid,</l>
               <l>My bogling Fancy boldly bid be gone,</l>
               <l>And thee, ill Fortune, leading, I go on.</l>
               <l>Into the Coach, yet with ſome hope, I ſtept,</l>
               <l>Not without all hope, for I hop'd t'have ſlept:</l>
               <l>Trepanning Fortune reſolv'd to neglect,</l>
               <l>I now apply'd to <hi>Somnus</hi> for effect;</l>
               <l>Invoke for a deep ſleep the pleaſant God;</l>
               <l>All pleaſure I cou'd hope for whilſt I rode;</l>
               <l>Begg'd that ſince <hi>Romans</hi> in a pet cou'd dye</l>
               <l>For Freedom, I might ſleep for Liberty.</l>
               <l>Like thoſe who go to <hi>Tyburn,</hi> on my way</l>
               <l>Then went, in hopes of Heaven the ſame day;</l>
               <l>Ty'd to a Coach and Company as good,</l>
               <l>As if I had been ſent to th' <hi>Triple Wood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As ſoon as we were off the jolting Stones,</l>
               <l>Firſt things they utter'd were ſome ſighs and groans,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100354:16"/>With Eyes turn'd up: The firſt ſhape they thought fit</l>
               <l>T' appear in, was it ſeems the Hypocrite.</l>
               <l>But then in Courteſie they all unmask</l>
               <l>Their Faces, but not Hearts. Oh too hard task,</l>
               <l>Too hard for
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Davus ſum, non Oedipus.</hi> Ter.</note> 
                  <hi>Davus,</hi> and much more for us;</l>
               <l>Scarce to b' interpreted by <hi>Oedipus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When Northern Madam 'gainſt the ſins of Man</l>
               <l>Spoke zealouſly, but the old Maid began</l>
               <l>'Gainſt ſingle life t' exclame, and did declare,</l>
               <l>That for her part, ſhe thought it a meer ſnare:</l>
               <l>Went on in Zeal, with Humour and with Grace,</l>
               <l>That made the moſt of a decaying Face.</l>
               <l>Much time this Virgin unawares had ſpent</l>
               <l>In ſowre Virginity, more than ſhe meant,</l>
               <l>Or thought to do; which oft ſhe did repent,</l>
               <l>Oft had allay'd with ſoft divertiſement;</l>
               <l>Much had in Body ſuffer'd, much in Mind,</l>
               <l>And much in Reputation for being kind.</l>
               <l>Now at her laſt effort, all ſhe cou'd do</l>
               <l>Was, on grave Motives, godlily to wooe.</l>
               <l>She prov'd, from God's own handy-work, that ſhe</l>
               <l>By Man's ſide always had a right to be:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100354:16"/>All Women thence firſt torn, (ſhe 'mongſt the reſt)</l>
               <l>By re-conjunction were all to be bleſt.</l>
               <l>She pleaded, as if forty Spirits mov'd,</l>
               <l>Had given her Impulſes to be lov'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And flew in carnal Godlineſs ſo high,</l>
               <l>She read upon <hi>Encreaſe and Multiply.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Stench'd with Love Theological, I choak,</l>
               <l>For meer ſelf-preſervation ſhould have ſpoke:</l>
               <l>But yet averſe from feminine diſpute,</l>
               <l>I 'admir'd the happy freedom of the Mute.</l>
               <l>Which ſcarce allow'd, I in my own defence,</l>
               <l>Declar'd ſor Liberty of Conſcience:</l>
               <l>Thought that the likelieſt, and the faireſt way</l>
               <l>To ſweet repoſe; at leaſt for one poor day.</l>
               <l>But flaxen Madam, younger much than ſhe,</l>
               <l>Was kindled at the name of Liberty:</l>
               <l>Lady indefinite, that of the many</l>
               <l>She'd ſeen, and known, was not in Love with any.</l>
               <l>Not this particular, but this, or that,</l>
               <l>Her Love impartially ſtill flying at.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>True Venus,</hi> Goddeſs like, ſtill unconfin'd,</l>
               <l>Immenſely was in Love with all mankind.</l>
               <l>This blazing Lady at a modiſh rate,</l>
               <l>Fleſh thus oppoſing Spirit, urg'd her Fate,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100354:17"/>And to the Lady who firſt ſilence broke,</l>
               <l>Theſe carnal thoughts ſhe elegantly ſpoke.</l>
               <l>Madam, your Plea is obſolete and vain,</l>
               <l>Quite out of faſhion, it leads back again</l>
               <l>To th' Houſe of Bondage, we're broke out from thence,</l>
               <l>The Spirit uſes now new Eloquence;</l>
               <l>Aloud amongſt the Godly daily crys</l>
               <l>For Liberty, and opening of our Eyes.</l>
               <l>In Matrimony Eyes are rather ſhut,</l>
               <l>At leaſt both Eyes with one poor Man you glut,</l>
               <l>To one alone ſo diſmally confin'd,</l>
               <l>That with Obedience you are ſtruck quite blind.</l>
               <l>The
<note n="*" place="bottom">This Objection againſt Marriage, made by a Miſtreſs, is anſwered by <hi>Acer,</hi> at the beginning of the Firſt Dialogue, in the Second Part of <hi>Metellus,</hi> &amp;c.</note> plea reduces to an evil thing,</l>
               <l>Enſlaves us to an Arbitrary King,</l>
               <l>With power abſolute to give us Law,</l>
               <l>And keep our Property ſtill under awe;</l>
               <l>Our ſo-long-enjoy'd Liberties invades,</l>
               <l>And ſpoils the ſweetneſs of our pleaſant Trades:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100354:17"/>And therefore, though't be holy, needs muſt be</l>
               <l>Still burdenſome to long-us'd Liberty.</l>
               <l>Ah! Pleaſure cannot any where be found,</l>
               <l>But where there's Liberty, does there abound.</l>
               <l>Suppoſe all Bleſſings that you can in Wife,</l>
               <l>Under confinement ſtill you lead your life;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now to a bleſſing to be chain'd and ty'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is for the Bleſſed to be Devilify'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beſides, in Wedlock there is many a grief:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All you're confin'd to, and without relief;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſoak in ſorrow, be conſum'd in ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Boyl with Contention, waſt away your life;</l>
               <l>To ſtew in Marriage thus for'ought we can tell,</l>
               <l>May be as bad as to be fry'd in Hell.</l>
               <l>You've too vain thoughts of the Infernal pain,</l>
               <l>Who thus compare it with thoſe griefs ye fain,</l>
               <l>Madam, ſaid I: much more I wou'd have ſaid,</l>
               <l>But our diſpute by Fate was ſtifled.</l>
               <l>For <hi>Rhadamanth</hi> had harraſſed our brains,</l>
               <l>With diſmal Jolts, and not unlike Hell's pains,</l>
               <l>Which came then thick upon us, and 'twas <hi>Ill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not only rugged, but repeated ſtill,</l>
               <l>Not likely e're to end, nor yet cou'd kill.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100354:18"/>We cou'd not on the Coachman's Rack diſpute,</l>
               <l>So, for ſome time, we all of us were mute.</l>
               <l>Reſolv'd, O <hi>Laelius,</hi> theſe things ſoon as we</l>
               <l>Met, to diſcourſe more thorowly with thee.</l>
               <l>But we at laſt came to a fairer way,</l>
               <l>Pleaſant and broad, yet ſtill down-hill all day,</l>
               <l>I think we went: by th' way no Man cou'd tell</l>
               <l>Nor Company, but we were going to Hell.</l>
               <l>The Coach-man like a <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi> ſate,</l>
               <l>Hurried us downward at ſuch Deviliſh rate,</l>
               <l>And uncontroulable, the Plea, Hold, Hold,</l>
               <l>Signify'd nothing, he was hot and bold.</l>
               <l>Th' inexorable fury was come on,</l>
               <l>His Breaſt by Ale, he whipt like <hi>Tiſyphon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">Digreſſion of Ale.</note> Ale a dull Liquor, where Hell's Brewers mix</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lethe</hi>'s forgetful Streams with muddy <hi>Styx.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Black Juice that does from blacker Furnace flow,</l>
               <l>('Tis thought the Nectar of the Gods below)</l>
               <l>The never-quenching Drink of thoſe abodes,</l>
               <l>The irritating Liquor of our Roads,</l>
               <l>That makes dull Coachmen ſtir, fat Burghers ſit,</l>
               <l>The more they drink, the more deſiring it.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100354:18"/>Some ſay 'twas <hi>Ceres</hi> Tears, when ſhe in grief</l>
               <l>Sought long in vain <hi>Proſerpina</hi>'s relief,</l>
               <l>Which mixt with <hi>Styx,</hi> and <hi>Lethe,</hi> ſtill in Hell,</l>
               <l>They drink to th' Honour of that Maid that fell</l>
               <l>To <hi>Pluto</hi>'s ſhare. —</l>
               <l>And ſome of <hi>Bacchus</hi> Faction too there be,</l>
               <l>Who ſay, with no leſs probability,</l>
               <l>'Tis the now black <hi>Proſerpina</hi>'s groſs ſweat,</l>
               <l>Caus'd in dark Shades by an Infernal heat,</l>
               <l>Thence ſent to us: But if a brisk Old Man,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Servant, hater of the Can,</l>
               <l>We will believe, if we may believe fame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ale</hi> firſt was Lake, Nymph who by <hi>Ceres</hi> came</l>
               <l>To be ennobled; eclips'd <hi>Bacchus</hi> Name,</l>
               <l>Oppos'd bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> Glory. Some groſs Cloud</l>
               <l>Threw oft on thoſe <hi>Apollo</hi> had endow'd:</l>
               <l>Hence the brown Nymph by angry <hi>Bacchus</hi> frown,</l>
               <l>Firſt was diſgrac'd, by <hi>Phoebus,</hi> then damn'd down</l>
               <l>To dark Abodes: Dwells ſince in Muddy Lakes</l>
               <l>Of dirty Towns, where the long hiſſing Snakes</l>
               <l>Infuſe their Venome: Taken with th' abode</l>
               <l>Of Croaking Frog, and of the Stygian Toad:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100354:19"/>Near ſome great Town ſhe ſtill environ'd lies,</l>
               <l>With Miſts and Foggs, whence, O whence no ſparks riſe</l>
               <l>Of Ingenuity. By 'infernal Flames</l>
               <l>Of Acherontick Coal, her Waters, Dames,</l>
               <l>Or Brewers, boil: by them convey'd, and ſold,</l>
               <l>They 'impower the old and ugly Queans to ſcold,</l>
               <l>Young Whores to hiſs: make all ill Women bold.</l>
               <l>This Drink clouds all Mens Brains, the darkned Mind</l>
               <l>By the groſs Nymph is to groſs Thoughts inclin'd.</l>
               <l>In common Men, does hideous Noiſes make,</l>
               <l>Reſembling Frogs, from whence it came, and Snake.</l>
               <l>On Market-days, the heavy Country Clown</l>
               <l>This rouzes up to moule his Landlord down.</l>
               <l>Hence firſt Rebellion hiſſes in the ſtreet;</l>
               <l>This makes the Uproar, makes the Rabble meet.</l>
               <l>This makes the blunt and brawny Carmen croke,</l>
               <l>And the exalted Coachman to provoke.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charon</hi>'s cold Tribe this fires, and makes 'em row,</l>
               <l>This makes 'em ſight, and give the fatal Blow.</l>
               <l>The foul <hi>Tartarean</hi> Bawd this does inſpire,</l>
               <l>And teaches her how to exalt her Hire.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:100354:19"/>This metamorphoſes at Country-Feaſt,</l>
               <l>The Common Man into the ſhape of Beaſt.</l>
               <l>To drunken Sow, turns th' Hoſteſs of the Town,</l>
               <l>And this turns Country-Gentleman to Clown.</l>
               <l>For theſe great Feats, Infernal <hi>Pluto</hi> makes</l>
               <l>This Nymph, they ſay, the Lady of all Lakes.</l>
               <l>Reſembling <hi>Styx;</hi> the Goddeſs of the Fen,</l>
               <l>Of Grains, of Swine, and of all ſwilling Men.</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand Furnaces to her do ſmoke</l>
               <l>In the dark North, where they great Cities choke.</l>
               <l>Nor does the Nymph delight in purer Flame,</l>
               <l>Well ſwollen Bellies do ſet forth her Name.</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Bacchus</hi> fails, in ſhape of double Jugg,</l>
               <l>This homely Goddeſs they are fain to hugg;</l>
               <l>Yet build no Temples, but adore in Tub</l>
               <l>The huge groſs Siſter of great <hi>Belzebub.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus ſpake the Poet, ſoaring in good Wine</l>
               <l>Above dull Ale, a Liquor leſs Divine.</l>
               <l>Had good <hi>Aeneas</hi> been a Pilgrim ſtill,</l>
               <l>And met us running down ſo ſteep a Hill</l>
               <l>As here we did, and to a Vale ſo low,</l>
               <l>What could he think, but that we meant to go</l>
               <l>To <hi>Pluto</hi>'s Regions, when we hurried ſo,</l>
               <l>With ſuch <hi>Proſerpina's?</hi> —</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100354:20"/>He muſt have complimented, without doubt,</l>
               <l>Furies within, and <hi>Rhadamanth</hi> without;</l>
               <l>Nor would have needed <hi>Sibyl,</hi> nor the Bough,</l>
               <l>To lead his Piety the right Way now,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Styx</hi> or <hi>Acheron;</hi> for we had Three</l>
               <l>As skilful <hi>Sibyls,</hi> who were all as free</l>
               <l>Of Hell, by' another <hi>Golden</hi> Myſtery.</l>
               <l>The Morning ſpent thus dolefully; Day gone</l>
               <l>Almoſt three Quarters, and Night coming on,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Se'n-Oak</hi>'s ſmall Town at laſt we ſtumble on.</l>
               <l>The Inn appear'd, and as ſoon as we came</l>
               <l>Within the door, and bonny Northern Dame,</l>
               <l>With help of Coachman, the good Hoſt had fixt</l>
               <l>In Elbow-Chair, with no ſmall State, betwixt</l>
               <l>Her two Companions; ſhe had wip'd off ſweat.</l>
               <l>Next care the Houſe had, was to let us eat.</l>
               <l>Hoſteſs and Hoſt advance, purſue us in,</l>
               <l>With all the Houſhold-Devils of an Inn.</l>
               <l>My Landlord, who in Compliments abounded,</l>
               <l>With Tapſter, Chamberlain, and Maids ſurrounded,</l>
               <l>Gave us of things both ord'nary and rare,</l>
               <l>A very Tantalizing Bill of Fare.</l>
               <l>But Northern Madam and her Dames afraid,</l>
               <l>The Burden of a Dinner would be laid</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100354:20"/>Too hard on them, who had no Gallant there,</l>
               <l>In Wiſdom thought it ſafeſt to forbear</l>
               <l>Their Hunger then; cry'd 'tis too late to eat,</l>
               <l>What ſhou'd they do with all that greaſie Meat?</l>
               <l>And wanted Stomachs too, but what was worſe,</l>
               <l>My Landlord fear'd a greater want in Purſe.</l>
               <l>And ſo in cold Deſpair ſoon turn'd his Back,</l>
               <l>Left his good Wife to make the next Attack.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Rhadamant</hi> grown ſierce, ſo vain excuſe</l>
               <l>Cou'd be 'gainſt him and Hunger, of no uſe:</l>
               <l>We join in Argument; what help, ſaid I?</l>
               <l>Theſe Devils here of Dinner-time, defie,</l>
               <l>By Nature faſting, we muſt eat or fly:</l>
               <l>The Coachman ſware, That he muſt eat, or dy.</l>
               <l>In hungry Rage I conjure down the Hoſt,</l>
               <l>Of ſqueamiſh Fairies, raiſe my Landlord's Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>Beſpeak a Dinner; whilſt they lay the Cloth,</l>
               <l>I call for Wine, and lay great <hi>Bacchus</hi> wrath.</l>
               <l>When Dinner came, in Courteſie we pray</l>
               <l>Landlord and Landlady, who ſcarce obey;</l>
               <l>Too full of bus'neſs; buſie with their Meat,</l>
               <l>"That foul, but great Employment of the great!</l>
               <l>Providing what to drink, and what to eat.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100354:21"/>But came at laſt. My N'oſt <hi>(hoping n'Offence)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>T'enflame the Reckning: ſhe with beſt pretence,</l>
               <l>To wait upon the <hi>Dames</hi> in our Defence.</l>
               <l>Of woolly Veniſon then came up a Loin:</l>
               <l>Two Rabbets next: we'allay with cheering Wine</l>
               <l>Bad Company: and plentifully dine.</l>
               <l>We'd done, and <hi>Rhadamant</hi> began to call,</l>
               <l>Dire <hi>Rhadamant,</hi> Determiner of all</l>
               <l>Our Time, and Paſtime, there was no Appeal,</l>
               <l>When black <hi>Ambroſia</hi> had once ſir'd his Zeal.</l>
               <l>The Reckoning came, and Northern Madam read</l>
               <l>A learned Lecture upon Beer and Bread,</l>
               <l>Then on the Meat, ſaying, Indeed ſhe could wiſh</l>
               <l>A longer time to debate every Diſh,</l>
               <l>With the ſharp Hoſteſs: but that not allow'd</l>
               <l>By <hi>Rhadamant,</hi> who call'd again aloud;</l>
               <l>A ſhort diſpute how we ſhou'd pay, aroſe:</l>
               <l>I offer all, but Madam too well knows</l>
               <l>What Honour is; ſhe preſſes, I obey:</l>
               <l>Allow her half the Honour of the day.</l>
               <l>Down ſtairs we come, take leave of <hi>Se'n-Oak</hi>-Town,</l>
               <l>A little place, and of a ſmall Renown,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100354:21"/>Unleſs remember'd for the firſt Approach</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Tunbridge</hi>-Fairies, who haunt every Coach,</l>
               <l>There firſt; fair Dippers, who come fourteen Mile</l>
               <l>To get a Promiſe, or a hopeful Smile,</l>
               <l>Of any Lady, or of ſome fine Man,</l>
               <l>To dip their Water for 'em, if they can.</l>
               <l>Theſe with Addreſſes we found at the door,</l>
               <l>We anſwer'd them with Smiles then, and no more,</l>
               <l>Leaving their farther Plea to th' Fountain's Head,</l>
               <l>Their ſweet Abode, there to be anſwered.</l>
               <l>We all took Coach, when <hi>Rhadamant</hi> had ſpoke</l>
               <l>Words of Command, and given the ſmart ſtroke;</l>
               <l>Away we're hurried by two ſtout, ſwift Pair</l>
               <l>Of excellent Horſes, neighing through the Air;</l>
               <l>And now we had ſome hopes that we might come,</l>
               <l>At laſt beyond Hell, to <hi>Elyſium.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Road was gravelly, the Way was wide,</l>
               <l>Enclos'd with Wood, and Paſture on each ſide;</l>
               <l>Green Paſtures here dreſt in their Flowers appear,</l>
               <l>There Fields of Corn, as much as Ground can bear,</l>
               <l>Commend the Soil, and propheſie the Year.</l>
               <l>Beyond th' Incloſure, far as you can ſee,</l>
               <l>Vaſt Woods, in looking wild, look pleaſantly:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100354:22"/>The Sun was chearful, and the Day was mild,</l>
               <l>The Birds rejoyc'd, and the whole Country ſmil'd,</l>
               <l>Welcoming of us all the way we went,</l>
               <l>With pleaſant Proſpect, or with fragrant Scent;</l>
               <l>Birds gave us wild, but ſweet, Divertiſement.</l>
               <l>But Pleaſure, like this World,'s too quickly gone,</l>
               <l>Not till we loſt it, known, or thought upon.</l>
               <l>For on a ſuddain we to <hi>Tunbridge</hi> came,</l>
               <l>For nothing memorable but the Fame</l>
               <l>Of ſome few <hi>Bridges,</hi> whence it has that Name.</l>
               <l>A low, a dirty, and ill-favour'd Town,</l>
               <l>On which well-wiſhing Travellers might frown;</l>
               <l>In Honour of the Country, wiſh it down.</l>
               <l>Ill-favour'd Street, ill-favour'd Houſes, Race</l>
               <l>Of People, that might ſuit with ſuch a Place:</l>
               <l>Yet in this ugly Place, was one fair Wife,</l>
               <l>One dainty Daughter, dreſs'd up to the Life.</l>
               <l>No Coach paſt here, but Homage ſtill was-paid</l>
               <l>Or to fine Miſtreſs, or to the fair Maid;</l>
               <l>But that fair Day both Beauties were diſplai'd.</l>
               <l>Fair Hoſteſs, delicately dreſs'd, and fine,</l>
               <l>(Far before <hi>Bear,</hi> or <hi>Bull,</hi> inviting Sign</l>
               <l>To Ale; though no great Token of good Wine.)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:100354:22"/>Firſt at the door; then made gentile Approach,</l>
               <l>With th' Inn-Retinue, and attack'd the Coach.</l>
               <l>Tapſter on one hand, in Blue Apron fine,</l>
               <l>And Lac'd Cravat, produc'd that, he call'd Wine.</l>
               <l>Daughter remarkable for coſtly Face</l>
               <l>To thoſe who call there, and for coſtly Lace</l>
               <l>She'd ſet it in; behind her Mother came,</l>
               <l>But not at all behind her in her Fame.</l>
               <l>The Mother march'd before: for both their ſakes,</l>
               <l>Went <hi>Gentlewoman-Sewer</hi> to her Cakes.</l>
               <l>We look, We ſnap, but ſtay as little while</l>
               <l>As wary Dogs do at the River <hi>Nile.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We call for Reckoning, find the low Expence</l>
               <l>Reach'd not that Day unto the <hi>Seeing-Sence:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>W'allow for Cakes and Ale, allow no more;</l>
               <l>So left the Beauty-Treat upon the Score.</l>
               <l>Wine we put by; "For where the Woman's ſine,</l>
               <l>"Where Tapſter's Drawer, no Wiſe Man drinks Wine.</l>
               <l>We pay, we go, ſtern <hi>Rhadamant</hi> gives Law</l>
               <l>T' his nimble Horſes with the Laſh: they draw</l>
               <l>Us quickly off from <hi>Tunbridge Remora.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We run the rugged Street, <hi>Rhadamant</hi> ſtill</l>
               <l>With Beauty ſir'd, and Ale, whips up the Hill.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:100354:23"/>The <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Dames tormenting of his Breaſt,</l>
               <l>Nor he, nor Horſes now have any Reſt.</l>
               <l>The metled Coachman, metled Horſes gain</l>
               <l>Soon th' eaſie Hill, and run us to the Plain.</l>
               <l>The Country opens, and a long, wild Heath</l>
               <l>Firſt entertains us there with purer Breath:</l>
               <l>Then gives a Proſpect, which with more Delight,</l>
               <l>Pleaſes the Eye, than where it loſes ſight.</l>
               <l>"Conducted to the fartheſt of its Sphere</l>
               <l>"By Nature, Nature recreates it there,</l>
               <l>"And treats it by the way too ev'ry where;</l>
               <l>"Feaſts it with Objects; ev'ry pleaſant Green</l>
               <l>"Which in the diſtant Woods and Fields are ſeen,</l>
               <l>"So ſoftly fill, ſo ſweetly pleaſe the Eye,</l>
               <l>"Sight does not, as in endleſs Proſpect, dye,</l>
               <l>"But ſatiates with the Variety.</l>
               <l>Nearer the Way, upon the Mother-Ground</l>
               <l>Of all choice Simples, Mother-Time is found,</l>
               <l>Adorn'd with forty ſorts of Flowers round;</l>
               <l>A little farther ſhelter'd with the Green</l>
               <l>And Shady Wood, ſome rarer Herbs are ſeen.</l>
               <l>Wood-Sorrel, wholſome Betony, does grow,</l>
               <l>"Which has more Vertues than <hi>Phyſicians</hi> know.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100354:23"/>Forty ſorts too, which the Old Woman well</l>
               <l>Knows, we in groſs diſcover by the Smell;</l>
               <l>With many more a <hi>Solomon</hi> might name,</l>
               <l>But not found in the Catalogue of Fame.</l>
               <l>Juſt by the ſide of this ſo pleaſant Way,</l>
               <l>Some Pye-bald Houſes ſtand, and ſtrangely gay,</l>
               <l>So differently colour'd, you would think</l>
               <l>Each Pane of Wall there, were to ſell you Drink.</l>
               <l>As ſlight, as if built only for one Day,</l>
               <l>Nor 'bove Three Months of Twelve can Men there ſtay</l>
               <l>For Wind and Weather; five Rooms ſcarce one Hearth,</l>
               <l>Of other Neceſſaries as great Dearth.</l>
               <l>Sure the wiſe Founder hardly could ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>'Twould ſtill be Summer there, when he built thoſe</l>
               <l>Fine Bowers for Houſes, but hop'd he might make</l>
               <l>A Twelve-month's Rent in Three; ſo ſave his Stake.</l>
               <l>Here we alight, and of the Price enquire,</l>
               <l>Having firſt view'd; but finding Week's Rent higher</l>
               <l>Than Month's at <hi>London,</hi> we ſoon thence retire;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100354:24"/>Leaving, as many had done, the dainty Houſe,</l>
               <l>For ſplendid Caſtle, to the Country Mouſe:</l>
               <l>We haſten thence, and not a hundred Yards,</l>
               <l>But we ſee more; fair Houſes ſtill of Cards.</l>
               <l>We view, and paſs; each pretty Three-month's Seat,</l>
               <l>Bound by Foundation to be Nine-months Cheat:</l>
               <l>We praiſe 'em yet, and for moſt ſine and fair</l>
               <l>Dwellings commend 'em to the <hi>Birds of th' Air.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>Rhadamant,</hi> now come within the Smell</l>
               <l>Of the good Ale, and the good Dames o'th' <hi>Well;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hurries us down with ſuch a furious ſpeed,</l>
               <l>He's <hi>Rhadamantine</hi> Galloper indeed.</l>
               <l>Juſt as the Kite that hov'ring in the Air,</l>
               <l>Falls, waving ſomething; And then pitches fair,</l>
               <l>Near the Outhouſes of ſome ſcatter'd Town,</l>
               <l>To ſnatch the Chicken for which he comes down.</l>
               <l>So tow'ring <hi>Rhadamant</hi> whirles down the Hill,</l>
               <l>Circling a little, and glorying in his Skill,</l>
               <l>Pitches and ſtops, at laſt, near a fair Way,</l>
               <l>And there expoſes his two Birds of prey,</l>
               <l>On a ſmall Platt betwixt the Church and <hi>Well;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The fitteſt place for the Impure to dwell;</l>
               <l>The fitteſt place for ſuch Pure Dames to ſell</l>
               <l>Hypocriſie. —</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100354:24"/>(Now only two; for th' Elder Laſs was lent</l>
               <l>By th' way for ſome Gentile Divertiſement)</l>
               <l>But two were here expos'd; they look about,</l>
               <l>Soon find an old and ugly Hovel out.</l>
               <l>Where a declining Lady of the Mode,</l>
               <l>Th' Mode not declining yet, lodg'd near the Road.</l>
               <l>A Houſe it was, if yet a Houſe; or Cave,</l>
               <l>Or ſuch a Houſe, as Savages might have.</l>
               <l>A place, that ſometimes entertain'd ſome Men,</l>
               <l>But was indeed but a foul Harpy's Den,</l>
               <l>Where, all come in, none whole come out agen.</l>
               <l>'Tis Death for Worth to come within the Door;</l>
               <l>Repute, if 't once come there, 's ne'er heard of more.</l>
               <l>Th' ignorant Traveller here unawares</l>
               <l>Oft falls into th' inhoſpitable Snares.</l>
               <l>Hither our Dames, by inſtinct led, wou'd go,</l>
               <l>They enter, meet; at ſight acquainted grow,</l>
               <l>By' apparent Sympathy each other know.</l>
               <l>Like Qualities appear in Eyes and Face;</l>
               <l>Words jump with words. "Oh! what enchanting Grace</l>
               <l>Has like to like? How ſweetly art thou bleſt,</l>
               <l>Villany, when thou jump'ſt too with Intereſt?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100354:25"/>The Proverb holds not here, though Two, nay Three</l>
               <l>Of the ſame Trade meet, yet they may agree.</l>
               <l>So greateſt Trades have taught, Rich <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church Row,</l>
               <l>Har'd <hi>Turn-ſtile,</hi> ſilken <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> too;</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Exchanges</hi> both; who from that Practice grow:</l>
               <l>All with Advantage, all together wooe</l>
               <l>Next Man that comes. So here to fair Trepan</l>
               <l>Fair Dames pretend. Catch ſhe, that beſt catch can.</l>
               <l>Thus ſettled are the excellenteſt Three</l>
               <l>That could be join'd in a Sorority.</l>
               <l>The once fam'd, and ſtill uſeful <hi>Rhodothe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fond <hi>Megara,</hi> cunning <hi>Tiſyphone.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The firſt was ſettled there, th' two laſt came in.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rhodothe</hi> match for forty Lads had been,</l>
               <l>Skilful in Sores of Love and Spots of Sin.</l>
               <l>Dame that had ſometimes amorous heats of Zeal,</l>
               <l>In which ſome Scars of Fame ſhe us'd to heal,</l>
               <l>Would any Crime conceal for the diſtreſs'd,</l>
               <l>Eſpecially when 'twas her Intereſt.</l>
               <l>Sometimes had Raptures, in which ſhe wou'd tell</l>
               <l>Abroad the dark Occurrences of Hell:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100354:25"/>All and more than ſhe knew: When Zeal and Wine</l>
               <l>Had rais'd her Breaſt to Fury not Divine.</l>
               <l>Dame, Age, and Uglineſs, from Toyls of Love</l>
               <l>Long ſince had eas'd: her Spirit now above</l>
               <l>The Pleaſure, not the trade, flown to the height</l>
               <l>Of black Deſpair, Remorſe had turn'd to Spight;</l>
               <l>A Pillar of ſalt Malice: had ſuch Touch</l>
               <l>Of a dire Sect too, that ſhe was ſo much,</l>
               <l>And great in th' Eyes of many Reverend Dames,</l>
               <l>She came to be Determiner of <hi>Fames.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What ſhe thought fit to ſay, or what ſhe wrote,</l>
               <l>The reſt wou'd very reverendly quote.</l>
               <l>Her Life was ſuch, ſhe was in Calumny</l>
               <l>Of undeniable Authority.</l>
               <l>And judging others Faults ſtill by her own,</l>
               <l>She was in Sins to that Perfection grown,</l>
               <l>She impos'd her own on any: ſhe had none.</l>
               <l>In ſhort, this holy <hi>Momus</hi> Off-ſpring cou'd</l>
               <l>Beſpatter what, and where, and whom ſhe wou'd.</l>
               <l>Theſe were the Three, but theſe Three were not all,</l>
               <l>Poetick Fury here might Furies call.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100354:26"/>In Hell w' have heard of ſome, but <hi>Tunbridge-Well</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> now a greater Siſterhood than Hell.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>metamorphos'd</hi> Virgins, who ſhreud Taſh,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Amours in vain come here to waſh.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> need they all be now juſt by ſuch Names</l>
               <l>As we give theſe, known; they're known by their Fames.</l>
               <l>And if not Furies all, yet all may be</l>
               <l>True Harpies in our modern Poetry.</l>
               <l>"A flutt'ring ſort of Dames, trepanning Race,</l>
               <l>"High-flying Women, that devour the place,</l>
               <l>"Beſpatter all the Banquets with Diſgrace.</l>
               <l>"Of, all Sorts theſe are, and ſome of every Sect,</l>
               <l>"Some of the <hi>Reprobates,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Elect,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Which in Debauch ſpeak all one <hi>Dialect.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All here in pleaſant Principles agree,</l>
               <l>Though not in ſowre ones, of Divinity.</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> nor ſowre <hi>Presbyter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>E'er thinks true Fleſh and Blood in Love can err.</l>
               <l>Whether Church erre or not, they follow ſtill</l>
               <l>In Love, th' inſtinct of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Free-will.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though for true Speculation, and Right,</l>
               <l>And Practice of our Pieties we ſight.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:100354:26"/>Yet all Perſwaſions do too oft agree,</l>
               <l>Here in the Practice of Impiety.</l>
               <l>Ill Women of all ſorts here hope to be</l>
               <l>Miſtreſs or Devil to 'every thing they ſee.</l>
               <l>All Hunt, all Court, if any chance to fail</l>
               <l>Of what all aim at, all by Nature rail.</l>
               <l>If you're acquainted once, like thoſe, you're gone,</l>
               <l>Whom
<note n="*" place="bottom">See <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s <hi>Sadduc. Triumph.</hi> Story of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> But.</note> Fairies ſnatch for being Companion.</l>
               <l>And gone to ſuch a Siſter-hood, as well</l>
               <l>New Poets think, out-ſtrips the old one's Hell.</l>
               <l>For all, that cruel Fate condemns to theſe,</l>
               <l>Are plagu'd as much, and have as little eaſe.</l>
               <l>Not only <hi>Tiſyphon,</hi> each Siſter makes</l>
               <l>Her Tongue a Whip here, of a thouſand Snakes.</l>
               <l>And though none of theſe wear the bloody Coat,</l>
               <l>Theſe <hi>Tiſyphons</hi> yet anger'd cut your throat.</l>
               <l>Th' Acquaintance kills; which yet if you wou'd fly,</l>
               <l>They'll ſhoot you flying, kill you with a Lye.</l>
               <l>Such as from <hi>David</hi>'s time, the wicked Darr.</l>
               <l>To murder in the dark the <hi>Right in Heart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100354:27"/>Some baſe Reproach, ſo either way ye dy</l>
               <l>By a <hi>Dilemma</hi> of Iniquity.</l>
               <l>Thus theſe ſweet Ladies paſs the Summer here,</l>
               <l>And do again at Winter grow as clear</l>
               <l>As <hi>London</hi> Fires can make 'em; here well try'd,</l>
               <l>But at return ſo Spiritually dy'd,</l>
               <l>Under Protection of ſome holy Sect,</l>
               <l>They turn again into the pure <hi>Elect;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To publick Shame, ſo private Intereſt</l>
               <l>Makes Saint of Quean, too oft amongſt the beſt.</l>
               <l>But if they're <hi>happy whoſe Iniquity</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is not imputed,</hi> happy then is ſhe</l>
               <l>'Bove all the Tribe of downright ſinful Lovers,</l>
               <l>Whoſe bleſt Amours ſhew of Religion covers. —</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Aeſculape</hi> ſtood up, and with ſome wrath</l>
               <l>Said, Horrid Journey, <hi>Acer,</hi> by my Troth.</l>
               <l>But thou hadſt ſome Diverſion now and then,</l>
               <l>And all has now well furniſhed thy Pen.</l>
               <l>But that which pleas'd us moſt, thou didſt ſo trace,</l>
               <l>So claw thoſe deviliſh Harpies of the Place,</l>
               <l>They'll tumble now ſure hence to Hell apace.</l>
               <l>This pretty Paradiſe, O may'ſt thou free,</l>
               <l>With thy Satyrick Ingenuity,</l>
               <l>From this foul and foeminean Enemy.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:100354:27"/>Then <hi>Laelius</hi> ſpake—</l>
               <l>Thou 'ſt ſhewn us, <hi>Acer,</hi> thy Satyrick Wit,</l>
               <l>Something of <hi>Encomiaſtick</hi> too with it.</l>
               <l>A Harpy here, alas! is not a Foe,</l>
               <l>With all its Feathers, proof againſt thy Blow.</l>
               <l>Though they car'd little for <hi>Aeneas</hi> Swords,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anchiſes</hi> Prayers, yet they'll feel thy Words.</l>
               <l>Harpies took this time, <hi>Wrong Sow by the Ear;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They'll tremble hereafter at a Poet here.</l>
               <l>But yet that younger Lady of the Coach,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acer,</hi> methinks deſerves no great Reproach.</l>
               <l>You promiſed but now to anſwer me</l>
               <l>In her behalf. O let me Champion be,</l>
               <l>In ſo delighful Cauſe. Moſt willingly,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acer</hi> reply'd. After day or two's reſt,</l>
               <l>Now 'tis too late, and I'm with Sleep oppreſt.</l>
               <l>All favour the Excuſe, loth to delay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acer</hi>'s Repoſe, adjourn'd from Night to Day.</l>
               <l>Third Day was ſet, but <hi>Aeſculape</hi> deſir'd,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Acer</hi> cruel Fortune had ſo tir'd,</l>
               <l>With Contraries to Wit, and we ſo late</l>
               <l>Had kept him up, repeating of his Fate;</l>
               <l>That <hi>Curio</hi>'d firſt ſurvey, and then reherſe</l>
               <l>That pleaſant Wildneſs in well poliſh'd Verſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100354:28"/>
                  <hi>Acer</hi> and <hi>Laelius</hi> not till the fourth Day</l>
               <l>Shou'd have their Dialogue: The Witts obey.</l>
               <l>Our Friends take leave, but merrily admire</l>
               <l>The Cottage firſt, and Hoſteſs, ſo retire.</l>
               <l>By this time the good Dame with Ale reviv'd,</l>
               <l>Something of a poor Lodging had contriv'd:</l>
               <l>We all good Beds, and all clean Linen had,</l>
               <l>Though all things poor, yet nothing that was bad:</l>
               <l>Far'd as well as the Rich, with fewer things,</l>
               <l>And in poor Beds ſlept better than great Kings.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="dialogue">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100354:28"/>
            <head>THE Second Dialogue.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Tunbridge-Wells</hi> AND Place Deſcribed.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Metellus.</speaker>
               <l>TWice ſince we came, we in this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle place</l>
               <l>Early had ſeen bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> chearing Face.</l>
               <l>And now the Sun within the Cottage door,</l>
               <l>Seen all the Morning long, ſhin'd there no more.</l>
               <l>Near ſhady Trees the horned Cattle ſtood,</l>
               <l>Beating off Flies, and chewing of the Cud,</l>
               <l>Horſes ſought ſhelter in the Neighbouring Wood.</l>
               <l>Sheep, holding down their Heads, together run,</l>
               <l>Expoſing their thick Fleeces to the Sun.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100354:29"/>The pretty Birds in leavy Groves were hid,</l>
               <l>Nor ſing they now, as ſome hours ſince they did.</l>
               <l>The old and younger Cocks begin to crow,</l>
               <l>And that 'twas Noon let their old Miſtreſs know.</l>
               <l>When the good Dame yet looking at the Sun,</l>
               <l>And ſeeing that the wonted ſpace was run,</l>
               <l>Which made the firſt half day, ſet on the Board</l>
               <l>Such Meats as her poor Cottage cou'd afford.</l>
               <l>We fed on Bacon, and on Coleworts well,</l>
               <l>And drank in Maple, Ale that did excel,</l>
               <l>Not Brewers mixture, but the drink of <hi>Tale,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Brisk Salutiferous Old Woman's Ale</l>
               <l>Soon as we'd Din'd, <hi>Curio</hi> took up his Lute;</l>
               <l>This ſaid he, <hi>Acer,</hi> now the beſt will ſuit</l>
               <l>With wearied minds, at this time of the day,</l>
               <l>And walking 'bout the Room began to play.</l>
               <l>He ſung of Ebbing and of Flowing Seas,</l>
               <l>And of that Power that does ſuch things as theſe,</l>
               <l>Whence Rivers come, and whence ſweet Fountains flow,</l>
               <l>And how their Origins we beſt may know;</l>
               <l>Almoſt two hours, (nor did we think it long)</l>
               <l>We'd ſate attentive to the Learned Song.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:100354:29"/>When <hi>Aeſculape</hi> and <hi>Laelius</hi> coming in</l>
               <l>Began to tell us at what Treat they'd been.</l>
               <l>The Heath-poult Critically they compare</l>
               <l>With other Fowl, what Wheat-ear was, how rare,</l>
               <l>They tell; and then commend the well-grown Fiſh,</l>
               <l>Reading us Lectures upon every Diſh,</l>
               <l>Admire at laſt the Plate, in which they eat</l>
               <l>And drank ſo ſplendidly, beyond the Meat:</l>
               <l>When <hi>Curio</hi> excellently thus began;—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Curio.</speaker>
               <l>"That Care, great <hi>Aeſculape</hi>'s ſcarce wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Man;</l>
               <l>"To be ſo great a Critick in good Meat,</l>
               <l>"And with ſuch Curioſity to eat.</l>
               <l>"Prodigal Luxury! how doſt thou waſte</l>
               <l>"The World in Dinners? At a Meal we taſte</l>
               <l>"The Sea and Air, nor are we yet content,</l>
               <l>"Unleſs we ſee too half the <hi>Continent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"O too ambitious hunger of the Great!</l>
               <l>"Who thus wou'd treat us with the ſight of Meat;</l>
               <l>"Nature's deſire, alas! is but to eat.</l>
               <l>"With many mock'd, with much choak'd up, we die,</l>
               <l>"Not for want of, but with Variety.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100354:30"/>"Were Health or Nature ask'd, which wou'd accord</l>
               <l>"To that vain-Glory of ſo ſplendid Board?</l>
               <l>"The Sick are not reliev'd with ſo much Wine,</l>
               <l>"Nor to be well, need we uſe Cups ſo fine.</l>
               <l>"The Drink's no wholſomer in Gold, than Wood,</l>
               <l>"And to the Thirſty the cold Stream's as good.</l>
               <l>"Great Courts the Cottage but in this excel,</l>
               <l>"That thoſe eat more, but theſe eat oft'ner well.</l>
               <l>"The great in their great Palaces have leſs,</l>
               <l>"Than the poor Cottage has, of happineſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aeſcul.</speaker>
               <l>Theſe Stoick thoughts, ſaid <hi>Aeſculape,</hi> do well</l>
               <l>Become thee, <hi>Curio,</hi> in this lowly Cell.</l>
               <l>But that which we came hither now to ſee,</l>
               <l>Is Landſcape of this Place, and drawn by thee.</l>
               <l>W'entreat thee therefore that thou would'ſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe,</l>
               <l>And give us Yeſterday's Survey in Verſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:100354:30"/>
               <head>The PLACE.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curio.</speaker>
                  <l>SInce 'tis your pleaſure, Wits, and you command,</l>
                  <l>'Twould be in me ill manners to withſtand.</l>
                  <l>Not many hours I had enjoy'd of reſt</l>
                  <l>In that ſweet habitation of the bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Where Solitude and Poverty to thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who there inhabit, give a ſound repoſe.</l>
                  <l>But freſh <hi>Aurore</hi> diſpos'd the World to light,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phoebus</hi> ariſing, baniſh'd from our ſight</l>
                  <l>The glimm'ring Moon, and every leſſer light;</l>
                  <l>Forcing my Window, importun'd my Eyes,</l>
                  <l>With chearful beams, invited me to riſe.</l>
                  <l>The Larks were up, already, mounted high,</l>
                  <l>And with their chearing Notes had fill'd the Sky.</l>
                  <l>The Sparrows chirp'd, the Thruſh and Blackbird ſung,</l>
                  <l>With Bird's ſweet Muſick all the Countrey rung.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Nature's ſoft Muſicians ſing and play</l>
                  <l>Thus round about me, without Fidlers pay,</l>
                  <l>More natural, leſs mere'enary than they;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:100354:31"/>I dreſs apace, not like the Men that woe;</l>
                  <l>But clap on Cloaths, as Men of buſineſs do.</l>
                  <l>Dreſs'd, I went forth, and took the path that brings</l>
                  <l>Me after a ſhort walk unto the Springs.</l>
                  <l>I croſs the wild, but ſweet, and pleaſant Heath;</l>
                  <l>And as I go, I quicken with the breath</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Air,</hi> perfum'd with freſh and fragrant Earth</l>
                  <l>Something deſcending, till at laſt I came</l>
                  <l>Unto that little place of ſo great fame;</l>
                  <l>The Walks and Wells of <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> which both joyn,</l>
                  <l>Rude, till of late beginning to be fine.</l>
                  <l>Each way you come, ſome new built Houſes ſtand,</l>
                  <l>You'd think ſome little City were at hand,</l>
                  <l>So plac'd, ſo pretty, that as you come down,</l>
                  <l>They look like Suburbs of ſome pleaſant Town.</l>
                  <l>Taverns appear at firſt, with coſtly Signs,</l>
                  <l>And better token of good Town, good Wines.</l>
                  <l>Through theſe Preliminaries then you go</l>
                  <l>To th' Upper Walk, divided with a Row</l>
                  <l>Of ſhady Trees, from that which is below.</l>
                  <l>Trees, which ſince any, pity there's ſo few:</l>
                  <l>Pity we give not th' Healthy Soil its due.</l>
                  <l>Doubtleſs if till'd, place that as well might bear.</l>
                  <l>All ſorts of Trees, as thoſe few we ſee there.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:100354:31"/>For that Omiſſion, Art makes this amends,</l>
                  <l>That this one Row of Trees both Walks defends</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Phoebus</hi> Beams, and ſomething from the Rain,</l>
                  <l>Art, it ſeems, here does nothing too in vain.</l>
                  <l>The Upper-Walk's a rich and pleaſant Street,</l>
                  <l>Gentile as any, more than any ſweet:</l>
                  <l>Where pleaſures of the Town and Country meet.</l>
                  <l>The Shops, like thoſe of fam'd St. <hi>Germain</hi>'s Fair</l>
                  <l>For Plate, for Sweet-Meats, but beyond for Air.</l>
                  <l>Nor in the choice of Ware wou'd be behind,</l>
                  <l>Might theſe ſuch Chapmen here, as there are, find,</l>
                  <l>Beyond that, and th' Exchange, in pleaſant ſhade,</l>
                  <l>Which always here by verdant Trees is made,</l>
                  <l>Far beyond both for Sights: The Buyer ſees</l>
                  <l>City in Countrey, <hi>Cheapſide</hi> among Trees.</l>
                  <l>Turn from the Shops, you ſee ſome pleaſant Hill:</l>
                  <l>Turn back, green Trees, which Complement you ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Bending their Heads, obliging you with ſhade;</l>
                  <l>To look into the Shops ſeem to perſwade.</l>
                  <l>The Shops not only entertain with Toys,</l>
                  <l>But th' Buyer there good Company enjoys;</l>
                  <l>Some by a well-contriv'd and happy chance,</l>
                  <l>Fortune, by Raffling, does to Plate advance,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:100354:32"/>At no great Hazard; theſe buy Gifts to ſend,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſell to give: All time with pleaſure ſpend.</l>
                  <l>Ah, were we ſo well govern'd in delights,</l>
                  <l>As moſt t' affect that place that moſt invites!</l>
                  <l>Amiable <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> how ſoon then might we</l>
                  <l>Make more than a St. <hi>Germain</hi>'s Fair of thee.</l>
                  <l>Decaying Trades revive by coming down,</l>
                  <l>Abroad enjoy the pleaſures of the Town.</l>
                  <l>'Midſt of the Trees <hi>Apollo</hi> has a Quire,</l>
                  <l>Nor can we, <hi>Phoebus</hi> chooſe, but here admire.</l>
                  <l>'Mong all thy excellencies theſe ſoft Arts</l>
                  <l>Of thine, with which thou recreat'ſt our hearts,</l>
                  <l>Eaſeſt our Cares, that ſick minds too here may,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt well ſet Tunes thy skilful Muſick play,</l>
                  <l>Chearfully paſs the Morning of each Day.</l>
                  <l>Our Bodies, Cryſtal Springs would cleanſe in vain,</l>
                  <l>To lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> purpoſe purifie the Brain,</l>
                  <l>Did not theſe Harmonies of <hi>Phoebus</hi> do</l>
                  <l>With them ſtill ſome part of the wonder too.</l>
                  <l>Nor is the Gentle God in pleaſure dear,</l>
                  <l>To thoſe who do frequent his Paſtimes here.</l>
                  <l>The ſmalleſt Sacrifice of half a Crown,</l>
                  <l>Offer'd by each at firſt, when they come down,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:100354:32"/>Propitiates that half year the skilful Quire,</l>
                  <l>Nor take they all that Summer other Hire.</l>
                  <l>But when theſe ſee bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> Rays decline,</l>
                  <l>And the gay Troop below no longer ſhine;</l>
                  <l>When Day grows ſhort, when Birds and they deſcry</l>
                  <l>Approaching cold, theſe Nightingales too fly</l>
                  <l>To warmer Regions, there their Fortune try.</l>
                  <l>This pleaſant Street is all the Morning long,</l>
                  <l>A great, gentile, and not unruly Throng;</l>
                  <l>A ſober Multitude of ev'ry Sort</l>
                  <l>Except the Mean, who ſeldom there reſort,</l>
                  <l>Epitome of Country, Camp, and Court;</l>
                  <l>Grave here till Noon, then go elſewhere to ſport.</l>
                  <l>Dire Sects may here of grim Devotion talk,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt Moderater-Men juſt by 'em walk.</l>
                  <l>Th' Enthuſiaſtick with his Brain as full</l>
                  <l>Of Fury as <hi>Geneva</hi> Pulpit-Bull,</l>
                  <l>Yet here walks quiet, peaceable and dull.</l>
                  <l>Here the unfortunate of Loſs complain,</l>
                  <l>Here rich Curmud geons plot t' encreaſe their Gain;</l>
                  <l>And here ſoft Lovers do each other chear,</l>
                  <l>Nor does Love find what can offend it here.</l>
                  <l>Beſt Independent Meeting; you may ſay,</l>
                  <l>Or ſing, or read, or meditate, or pray.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:100354:33"/>Each as inſpir'd; and thô you 'have not that Grace,</l>
                  <l>The Muſick makes it yet a Heavenly Place.</l>
                  <l>The Underwalk runs parallel with this,</l>
                  <l>But ſomething lower, and of lower Bliſs;</l>
                  <l>Place Rural Gods did not intend to bleſs</l>
                  <l>With more, it ſeems, than <hi>Market</hi>-Happineſs.</l>
                  <l>Deſign'd to be but <hi>Larder</hi> to the great</l>
                  <l>And nobler Walk; <hi>Fair Magazine of Meat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O, were I Painter now, how well cou'd I</l>
                  <l>Deſcribe this pretty Market to the Eye?</l>
                  <l>But Airy Language cannot ſhew ſo well,</l>
                  <l>Nor what's bought, nor how prettily they ſell.</l>
                  <l>There is a Row of Trees that does divide</l>
                  <l>The Upper Walk and Lower: There the Pride</l>
                  <l>Of City ſtands: the Country here abide</l>
                  <l>In Walk, though Low, as pleaſant and as plain</l>
                  <l>As th' other is, but ſitter for the Swain.</l>
                  <l>Great numbers here of well-clad People ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Both Men and Women; none with empty hand;</l>
                  <l>Each brings you Dainties: Dainties you command,</l>
                  <l>At a low Price: when you have pleas'd your Eye,</l>
                  <l>With ſight of Plenty' as eaſily you buy.</l>
                  <l>The niceſt ſtomachs at no Market find</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>England,</hi> ſooner Dainties to their Mind.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:100354:33"/>Wheat-Ears and Quails which every where are ſought,</l>
                  <l>Here are the oftneſt and the cheapeſt bought.</l>
                  <l>Heath-poult and Pheaſant, ev'ry thing the Year</l>
                  <l>And Seaſon can afford, they' afford you here.</l>
                  <l>The Lady, without wetting of her Shooe,</l>
                  <l>May chuſe her Dinner, while her Gallants wooe.</l>
                  <l>Appears more lovely in the low Employ,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt the' amorous Friend preſents the welcome Toy:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Bisket or the Country Cake</l>
                  <l>Which with great Care here cleanly Houſwifes make</l>
                  <l>So well, That they with City Palates take.</l>
                  <l>Baskets of choiceſt Fruits the Gallants bear</l>
                  <l>To Ladies hence; fair Preſents and not dear.</l>
                  <l>Excellence, ſuch Gifts no where have, but here</l>
                  <l>The want of Garden is ſo well ſupply'd,</l>
                  <l>No Fruit is to the' Inhabitants deny'd.</l>
                  <l>The Market's Garden, where though none can ſow,</l>
                  <l>None need to plant, none take the pains to mow.</l>
                  <l>All Crops all reap: All Fruits ſeem there to grow.</l>
                  <l>As fair as well-prun'd Trees this untill'd Field</l>
                  <l>The beſt of Fruits does without Gardiner yield.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:100354:34"/>Under the fragrant Leaves of yonder Trees</l>
                  <l>You ready gather'd find freſh Strawberries.</l>
                  <l>With Odoriferous Raſps, beneath that Tree</l>
                  <l>Shaded with Poplar Leaves you Cherries ſee,</l>
                  <l>As freſh as if they grew there, but more rare,</l>
                  <l>As if juſt grown, where none grow, they appear.</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Kent</hi>'s the Garden, this fair place may be</l>
                  <l>Call'd with great Reaſon <hi>Kent</hi>'s <hi>Epitome.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Kent</hi> all conſpires to feed ye, the beſt Plum,</l>
                  <l>Beſt Pears they have, from their beſt Gardens come.</l>
                  <l>Women, not more ambitious to ſell</l>
                  <l>Than to be ſeen, are all of 'em dreſs'd well,</l>
                  <l>In plain, but moſt becoming Country Clothes;</l>
                  <l>Plain Modeſty, adorning more than thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Sets of the Rural Nymphs, and makes 'em ſhow</l>
                  <l>Beyond what City Art or Coſt can do.</l>
                  <l>Beauty in Cities is diſguis'd, but here</l>
                  <l>The Goddeſs does without her Maſque appear.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="bottom">Digreſſion to Ladies who uſe Art.</note> Hence, O hence learn, ye Beauties of the Court,</l>
                  <l>And, ye fair Citizens, who here reſort,</l>
                  <l>At how much cheaper Rate you may be fine,</l>
                  <l>And how ye may reſtore thoſe Looks Divine,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:100354:34"/>Which that great God, that made you, did beſtow,</l>
                  <l>But now no veſtige here of his can know.</l>
                  <l>Too vain thoſe Arts are which teach thus to dreſs,</l>
                  <l>They do but make, what Nature gave you, leſs.</l>
                  <l>Ye hide in borrow'd Looks the nobleſt Part</l>
                  <l>Of God's beſt Work, diſparaging his Art.</l>
                  <l>Can Women's Art great Nature's Skill out-do?</l>
                  <l>What, 'bove fair Nature, can in Woman wooe?</l>
                  <l>Pictures, not Beauties, ye aſpire to be;</l>
                  <l>Men wou'd not th' Artificial Woman ſee,</l>
                  <l>But that which Nature fram'd, your ſelf in you,</l>
                  <l>Nor can they be in Love, but with the true.</l>
                  <l>Nature forbids: Men naturally hate</l>
                  <l>All in Mankind that is Sophiſticate.</l>
                  <l>Colour's not all the Beauty of the Face</l>
                  <l>That renders amiable our Humane Race.</l>
                  <l>Our Nature is with more Perfection ſeen</l>
                  <l>In the ſweet Humour, and the taking Meen,</l>
                  <l>And ſparkling Wit, live Features from within</l>
                  <l>Shining, than in an Artificial Skin.</l>
                  <l>O ye, that have ſuch Gifts as thoſe, diſgrace</l>
                  <l>Not Nature thus by a <hi>Pigmalion</hi> Face.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:100354:35"/>True Love's not gain'd by Face which Art has made,</l>
                  <l>Nor can thoſe artificial Looks perſwade.</l>
                  <l>Affection's natural: whom ye abuſe;</l>
                  <l>Nature it is that muſt True Love infuſe;</l>
                  <l>Who' in this new <hi>Eden</hi> ſurely muſt have meant</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adam</hi>'s loſt Paradiſe to repreſent.</l>
                  <l>And if the World at firſt from Atomes came,</l>
                  <l>Why may n't theſe Atomes here too do the ſame</l>
                  <l>In this ſmall World? —</l>
                  <l>By accidental Concourſe, give us twice</l>
                  <l>The Happineſs of earthly Paradiſe?</l>
                  <l>A Thought more probable, <hi>Lucrece,</hi> than thine,</l>
                  <l>Excellent Poet, but prophane Divine.</l>
                  <l>Here are the Rarities of that bleſt Place,</l>
                  <l>Theſe look like Primitives of Humane Race;</l>
                  <l>Here's <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt Felicity, nay, more,</l>
                  <l>They' have ſomething <hi>Adam</hi> had not heretofore:</l>
                  <l>No Mortal here, for Fruit he eats, is chid,</l>
                  <l>Or Meat; no Meat or Fruit is here forbid.</l>
                  <l>Better then, from this Concourſe, Paradiſe</l>
                  <l>May, than the World cou'd, from ſmall Atomes, riſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:100354:35"/>Beyond this Walk, but on a lower Ground,</l>
                  <l>Butchers, ſcarce ſeen from hence, are to be found,</l>
                  <l>In little, but clean Shops, where they conceal</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt Mutton, as good Beef, white Veal,</l>
                  <l>And Lamb, from Fly, and you; leſt ere you eat,</l>
                  <l>Your Stomach dine, cloy'd with the ſight of Meat.</l>
                  <l>'Soon as you come, the bloody Merchants ſmile,</l>
                  <l>And in their pleaſant ſanguinary Stile,</l>
                  <l>Tell of what Mutton they are there the Death,</l>
                  <l>That woolly Veniſon of their fragrant Heath,</l>
                  <l>Which, had it but its due, ought to be here</l>
                  <l>Preferr'd before the Wild and Fallow Deer.</l>
                  <l>In Rural Eloquence they' expreſs as well</l>
                  <l>Savo'ry Perfections of their Beef and Veal.</l>
                  <l>But ſo accommodating this rough Trade</l>
                  <l>By ſweet Place, and ſweet Intereſt is made;</l>
                  <l>That for ſmall Money, and ſome Amity,</l>
                  <l>To ſit you, they'll divide one Joint in three.</l>
                  <l>Help with fair Words the Bargain: make an end</l>
                  <l>With ſmooth Prognoſtick how their Meat will ſpend.</l>
                  <l>On one ſide of this Walk, Fiſh always ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And not far off, on a dry Platt of Sand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:100354:36"/>So freſh, they' offend no Noſe; the Eye they pleaſe</l>
                  <l>To ſee on ſo dry Land ſuch Fiſh as theſe.</l>
                  <l>All ſorts are ſold; all ſorts of Men here buy:</l>
                  <l>All Appetites vote Uniformity.</l>
                  <l>With Popiſh Conſcience godly Stomachs join,</l>
                  <l>As well as thoſe, on Crab and Lobſter, dine.</l>
                  <l>Though not ſo well affected to the Chair</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Peter;</hi> yet in Appetite keep fair</l>
                  <l>With Brethren of the Trade; the Popiſh Meat</l>
                  <l>Proteſting 'gainſt the' Injunction, they may eat:</l>
                  <l>To' advance on good Conſiderations,</l>
                  <l>Not <hi>Peter</hi>'s Inte'reſt but the Nation's.</l>
                  <l>The Lobſter, Oyſter, and the Crab, we ſee</l>
                  <l>Good honeſt Heathens eat as well as we.</l>
                  <l>"But 'tis Religion that is nought with Fiſh;</l>
                  <l>"What need the day preſcribe to us the Diſh?</l>
                  <l>Now Superſtition is all caſt behind,</l>
                  <l>If we' eat but what, and when we have a mind.</l>
                  <l>Shell-fiſh created ſeems, for wary Houſe,</l>
                  <l>By Nature wears its Cupboard 'gainſt the Mouſe.</l>
                  <l>Two or three days untouch'd, till Dame command,</l>
                  <l>Or have a mind, conveniently they ſtand;</l>
                  <l>Then are eat ſavingly, boyl'd to their hand.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:100354:36"/>Theſe Fiſh, no wonder if the Godly ſpend</l>
                  <l>For publick Intereſt, and private end;</l>
                  <l>But ſuperſtitious
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Haddock</hi> has Spots on either ſide, which are ſaid, marks of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Fingers, when he catch'd that Fiſh for the Tribute.</note> 
                     <hi>Haddock,</hi> which appear</l>
                  <l>With marks of <hi>Rome,</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Finger's here,</l>
                  <l>I wondred more to find amongſt th' Elect,</l>
                  <l>And ſo Predeſtinated to the Sect.</l>
                  <l>Twice ſnatcht from us to feed the godly Man,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we poor wicked ſtarve by the Trepan.</l>
                  <l>O ſuperſtitious Dainty, <hi>Peter</hi>'s Fiſh,</l>
                  <l>How com'ſt thou here to make ſo godly Diſh?</l>
                  <l>And yet ſuch Fiſh as theſe can't ſafely dine</l>
                  <l>The Lady whom Religion does confine.</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt Church and Fathers, if Phyſician join,</l>
                  <l>With Appetite, the plauſibler Divine.</l>
                  <l>Behind this Market on a riſing ground,</l>
                  <l>Under the Hill a pretty Houſe I found,</l>
                  <l>Not finiſh'd yet, yet that did give us then,</l>
                  <l>Of what it wou'd be no ſmall Specimen.</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſituated where the pleaſant Vine</l>
                  <l>It ſelf wou'd flouriſh; well deſign'd for Wine.</l>
                  <l>The Houſe invited, and the Wine as much,</l>
                  <l>The Maſter more; I wiſh all Vintners ſuch.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:100354:37"/>Merchant, with whom Friends and fine place pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd,</l>
                  <l>That here by' himſelf his Wine might be retail'd;</l>
                  <l>Gentile young Man, if Fortune deal as well</l>
                  <l>As Nature with him, born to give, not ſell.</l>
                  <l>The Drawer pleas'd, but above all the Cook,</l>
                  <l>Skillful and pleaſant by' Art and Nature, took.</l>
                  <l>Here I meet Friends; and here, though late, we dine,</l>
                  <l>And here we ſtew new Fiſh in good old Wine.</l>
                  <l>We well were treated both in Wine and Fare,</l>
                  <l>And in fair Reckonings, a great deal more rare.</l>
                  <l>Hence I croſs'd back through th' Market, to the end</l>
                  <l>Of th' Upper Walk, thence to the Wells deſcend.</l>
                  <l>Theſe, <hi>Acer,</hi> I familiarly rehearſe,</l>
                  <l>This ſubject bearing not a higher Verſe.</l>
                  <l>"Where th' Objects are unequal, lye ſo low,</l>
                  <l>No Fancy there to any height can go.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Acer</hi> reply'd.</stage>
                  <l>It is the greateſt Art</l>
                  <l>To humour th' Object: That makes Verſe both ſmart</l>
                  <l>And elegant. Therefore with more delight</l>
                  <l>We've heard this Verſe, than if 't had flown to height.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:100354:37"/>But now thou 'rt at the Wells, let fancy go</l>
                  <l>To higher ſtrain, ſmooth like the Fountain flow.</l>
                  <l>We all of us ſhall think it worth our while,</l>
                  <l>To hear Wit with variety of Stile.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curio.</speaker>
                  <l>Too much, O Friends, ye now expect from me,</l>
                  <l>That give me ſuch a Task of Poetry.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Curio</hi> reply'd, at this time of the day;</l>
                  <l>But if you'll have it, and I muſt obey,</l>
                  <l>O, be thou then my <hi>Helicon,</hi> inſpire,</l>
                  <l>Prodigious Fountain, thy ſteel'd ſtreams have fire.</l>
                  <l>I' have drunk: the' inſpiring draught compels to fly,</l>
                  <l>And th' force of this new <hi>Helicon</hi> to try.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The WELLS.</head>
               <sp>
                  <l>BEyond the pleaſant Street, that ſhady Row</l>
                  <l>Of Greeneſt Trees, confronting Shops; below</l>
                  <l>That gloomy Walk, there is ſome ſandy ground,</l>
                  <l>With Heath, and Rocks, and Hills encompaſs'd round.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:100354:38"/>Yet not too high, too horrid, nor too near,</l>
                  <l>But at a diſtance, as if with ſome fear,</l>
                  <l>And Reverence, Rocks ſtood admiring there.</l>
                  <l>In mid'ſt of Rocks, within that ſandy ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Fam'd <hi>Well,</hi> the ancient Mother of that place,</l>
                  <l>Nature has plac'd; from her at firſt the name</l>
                  <l>Of the ſmall Village, and from her the Fame:</l>
                  <l>From her, th' Inhabitants and Houſes came.</l>
                  <l>Had ſhe of old done, what ſhe now has wrought,</l>
                  <l>She wou'd by th' Ancients have been Goddeſs thought.</l>
                  <l>But with more truth the wiſe contemplate now</l>
                  <l>His Finger there, to whom all Mortals bow.</l>
                  <l>Angels of old, when God from Heaven ſent</l>
                  <l>To Cure us, yet 'twas by this Element.</l>
                  <l>Though Cures were then by Angels to be wrought,</l>
                  <l>The Paralyticks to the Pool were brought.</l>
                  <l>With greater grandeur powerful God does here</l>
                  <l>In Nature, his great Subſtitute, appear,</l>
                  <l>Now in theſe Fountains, than by Angels there.</l>
                  <l>Nature, the Soul of the great World, we ſee</l>
                  <l>Demonſtrating here the Divinity.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ſhe ſupported by th' Almighty hand,</l>
                  <l>Works daily wonders by great God's Command.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:100354:38"/>And whether we admire her by the Name</l>
                  <l>Of Goddeſs, God, or Nature, 'tis the ſame.</l>
                  <l>We ſee Effects that can be none but his,</l>
                  <l>Adore great God in what great Nature is:</l>
                  <l>Who e'er thou art, that on us Men below,</l>
                  <l>Such Gifts as theſe art able to beſtow,</l>
                  <l>In thee ſure ſome Immortal Powe'r muſt live,</l>
                  <l>None but the' Omnipotent ſuch Gifts can give;</l>
                  <l>Nature is but God's Repreſentative.</l>
                  <l>Conceal'd, yet known; Inviſible ſhe ſits,</l>
                  <l>Appearing to us but in Benefits:</l>
                  <l>By great Effects, as God is wont to do,</l>
                  <l>(For God in Nature appears greatly too.)</l>
                  <l>Here Goddeſs-like, though under Fountain's Name,</l>
                  <l>She does thoſe Wonders which give Fountains Fame.</l>
                  <l>Plac'd with her Back to the wide Heath and Hills,</l>
                  <l>As 'if conſcious that her Buſi'nefs were our Ills,</l>
                  <l>She looks into the Walks, where ſplendid Throng</l>
                  <l>Of Patients do attend all Summer long.</l>
                  <l>Theſe all the Morning from that pleaſant Place</l>
                  <l>She daily does receive with open Face.</l>
                  <l>Wall'd in, whether for Beauty, or for State,</l>
                  <l>Or both, ſhe always keeps an open Gate;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:100354:39"/>Thro' which ſhe ſees that Crowd of Patients walk;</l>
                  <l>And ſeems to hearken how the' afflicted talk;</l>
                  <l>When they declining groan, when they complain,</l>
                  <l>Hence ſhe ſends Water that revives again.</l>
                  <l>Twice twenty Nymphs ſtill round about her ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Fair Country Maids, each with a Glaſs in hand,</l>
                  <l>Reaching her Bounty forth, give with good Grace.</l>
                  <l>Full Cups, beſtow'd by th' Goddeſs of the Place.</l>
                  <l>Here ſits her Power, and hence her Bounty flows,</l>
                  <l>And hence a Torrent of her Kindneſs goes,</l>
                  <l>Encreaſing ſtill, extending the ſmall Flood,</l>
                  <l>As if ambitious to diffuſe the Good</l>
                  <l>Through the dry Valley of that ſcorched Heath,</l>
                  <l>Prolongs Life there, and ſaves from cruel Death.</l>
                  <l>Cures ſomething ſtill, though not Men as at firſt,</l>
                  <l>Saves pining Cattle from the Plague of Thirſt.</l>
                  <l>Something in Virtue at a diſtance leſs,</l>
                  <l>But Fountain every where ordain'd to bleſs.</l>
                  <l>Whether her Learned Doctours thought the fair</l>
                  <l>Fountain ſhou'd ſo have Benefit of Air,</l>
                  <l>Or Favourite of Heaven, it was fit</l>
                  <l>It ſhou'd have Way to' Heave'n, and Heav'en to it.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:100354:39"/>This Divine Fountain, though 'tis walled in,</l>
                  <l>Yet has no Covering: ſtill by Heaven ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Still Heaven ſees: beholds each glorious Star,</l>
                  <l>Of which it feels the Influence ſo far.</l>
                  <l>But, O ye Muſes all, inſpire me now,</l>
                  <l>That I the Bowels of the Earth may plow;</l>
                  <l>Too hard a Task for any Muſe alone,</l>
                  <l>Requires more Powe'r than all the Nine dare own.</l>
                  <l>Too dark thoſe Paths are, for a Muſe to fly,</l>
                  <l>The Secret's ſcarce reach'd by Philoſophy.</l>
                  <l>Whether they only Luminaries are,</l>
                  <l>That can produce a Miracle ſo rare,</l>
                  <l>Or, by a Powe'r Divine, ſome brighter Star</l>
                  <l>Does pierce ſo deep, and influence ſo far;</l>
                  <l>From the dark Caverns of Eternal Night</l>
                  <l>And Earth, this Spring comes firſt; but Face ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>Such Excellencies has, it can't but be</l>
                  <l>From ſomething more than earthly Pedigree.</l>
                  <l>Our Common Mother, though ſhe had a ſhare</l>
                  <l>In the great Geniture, yet Birth ſo rare</l>
                  <l>Claims God or Star for Parent; here are two</l>
                  <l>Such Works as theſe, or God or Heave'n muſt do.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:100354:40"/>Whether that God that rules both Sea and Land,</l>
                  <l>From Seas firſt ſent theſe Waves by his Command,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe by frequent Showres from above</l>
                  <l>Well purify'd they come; the Star of Love,</l>
                  <l>Great Governneſs of amiable things,</l>
                  <l>Some Powe'r muſt needs have on theſe lovely Springs.</l>
                  <l>By her ſweet Conduct they ſo ſoftly flow,</l>
                  <l>And by her Softneſs they delight us ſo.</l>
                  <l>Her Kindneſs leads 'em gently through the Ground,</l>
                  <l>Brings 'em to <hi>Mars</hi> his Steel, that makes 'em ſound.</l>
                  <l>The powe'rful Luminaries both here join,</l>
                  <l>And in the Caverns of the Earth combine,</l>
                  <l>To influence the Salutife'rous Flood,</l>
                  <l>So great a Medi'cine, and ſo great a Good.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mars</hi> with Coeleſtial Heat warms from above,</l>
                  <l>The lowly Wave receives Coeleſtial Love.</l>
                  <l>She gently ſteals it through the Parent's Veins,</l>
                  <l>Seeking the Light, and as it goes, it gains,</l>
                  <l>Imbibes the Tincture of the powe'rful Steel,</l>
                  <l>Sweet Waves and healthful, <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> feel.</l>
                  <l>By her they cool and moiſten the hot Vein,</l>
                  <l>He with his Warmth enlivens them again.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:100354:40"/>The ſtubborn Steel affects the Water ſo,</l>
                  <l>The Waters temper that too as they go,</l>
                  <l>Till here at laſt both Luminaries bring</l>
                  <l>Out of the Earth this wonder-working Spring.</l>
                  <l>Ill-natur'd Earth! how cou'dſt thou ſo long hide</l>
                  <l>Such Powe'rs as theſe? Was 't thine, or Nature's Pride?</l>
                  <l>Cou'd ſhe, our Miſtreſs, thou a Parent bee?</l>
                  <l>Not for ſo many Ages let us ſee</l>
                  <l>This Antidote of our Mortality?</l>
                  <l>Or was Nature afraid that we ſhou'd live</l>
                  <l>Beyond her Limits, therefore wou'd not give?</l>
                  <l>What-ever 'twas, ye both kept ſecret long;</l>
                  <l>Though you bleſs now, ye did paſt Ages wrong.</l>
                  <l>Nature of Secret ſurely was too ſhy,</l>
                  <l>For ſo great Miſtreſs of Morality,</l>
                  <l>And of thee, Earth, thy Children ſure deſerv'd,</l>
                  <l>That that Life which thou gav'ſt, ſhou'd be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd.</l>
                  <l>But thou, great God, that ſaw'ſt much more than we,</l>
                  <l>Know'ſt more than Earth or Nature cou'd foreſee,</l>
                  <l>Reſerv'd'ſt this Medi'cine, like good Wine, till laſt,</l>
                  <l>Saw'ſt no ſuch need of it in Ages paſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:100354:41"/>Now is the Time Chalybeates ſhou'd be ſeen,</l>
                  <l>The World devolv'd is to an Age of Spleen,</l>
                  <l>Beyond that ſo long talkt of Iron Age,</l>
                  <l>A Time that brings forth ſuch a ruſty Rage,</l>
                  <l>As none of the known Medi'cines can aſſwage.</l>
                  <l>This ſaving Fountain ſurely comes at length</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Venus</hi> Beauty, and with <hi>Mars</hi>'s Strength,</l>
                  <l>To cleanſe and mollifie; from Heaven ſent</l>
                  <l>Plenipotentiary of the' Omnipotent.</l>
                  <l>She with her Sweetneſs makes th' hard Potion pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>And gently ſoftens the moroſe Diſeaſe.</l>
                  <l>He does his Strength 'gainſt tough Diſeaſes try,</l>
                  <l>Till with his tougher Steel he makes 'em fly.</l>
                  <l>Fountain impower'd by both's ordain'd to cure,</l>
                  <l>As far as Mortal Bodies can endure.</l>
                  <l>O might ſuch Stars work on our Morals too,</l>
                  <l>And on our Minds yet greater Wonders do!</l>
                  <l>But metamorphos'd <hi>Mars,</hi> why is't that thou</l>
                  <l>From God of War turn'ſt here Phyſician now?</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we turn Ploughs to Swords, here how comes all</l>
                  <l>The Steel thou mak'ſt to be ſo medi'cinal?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:100354:41"/>Waſt thou to Mortals ſo ſevere of old,</l>
                  <l>That their Devotion was almoſt grown cold,</l>
                  <l>Now with more grateful, and more God-like Skill,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe, thou ſav'ſt more, than thou 'rt wont to kill?</l>
                  <l>Or is't, That Men grown worſe than heretofore,</l>
                  <l>Need thy old Skill in Villany no more,</l>
                  <l>But Artiſts grown, can kill, can rob, can lye,</l>
                  <l>Without the help of Devi'l or Deity?</l>
                  <l>Or rather is 't, That we of late endure</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Plagues of <hi>Mars,</hi> no Drugg, but Steel can cure;</l>
                  <l>Which Divine Providence now to aſſwage</l>
                  <l>Prepares, by thee, ſome Antidote for the' Age?</l>
                  <l>And with that Sword of thine that hurt before,</l>
                  <l>At laſt deſigns to cure a great deal more.</l>
                  <l>What-ever 'tis in Mixture ſo Divine,</l>
                  <l>Some greater Work, great God muſt ſure deſign,</l>
                  <l>As much as the' Ancients, <hi>Aeſon,</hi> ſaid of thee,</l>
                  <l>This Fountain does, renews us bodily:</l>
                  <l>Like Ghoſts at firſt we here the living meet,</l>
                  <l>Muffled in Cap, cloak'd in long Winding-ſheet,</l>
                  <l>If yet alive, not like the living go,</l>
                  <l>As if they liv'd whe'er Nature wou'd or no.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:100354:42"/>Like Spi'rits they look; hollow, like Ghoſts, they talk,</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the living, juſt like dead Men, walk.</l>
                  <l>When on a ſuddain a ſtrange Change is made,</l>
                  <l>They flouriſh all who did ſo lately fade.</l>
                  <l>As if the Fountain had a Power to call</l>
                  <l>Back from the dead, they who ſeem'd buried all</l>
                  <l>Walk and ariſe from living Funeral.</l>
                  <l>In all parts of the Body <hi>Omens</hi> are,</l>
                  <l>That Strength and Health now openly declare.</l>
                  <l>All Symptoms change, the late weak Pulſe grows ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>All Parts reviv'd give hopes of living long:</l>
                  <l>No ſooner we imbibe the God-like Flood,</l>
                  <l>But Vitals all revive; corrupted Blood</l>
                  <l>Obſtructed, which for want of paſſage ſtood</l>
                  <l>Stagnant almoſt, new Spirits now make good.</l>
                  <l>The Spleen is cleans'd, the Liver open'd ſo,</l>
                  <l>To reinforce all Parts the Blood does go:</l>
                  <l>Each Limb partakes, and now that Vigour comes,</l>
                  <l>To every Part, that every Part becomes:</l>
                  <l>Whole Man renew'd, ſeems to be born again,</l>
                  <l>In the New Man no Place has the old Pain.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:100354:42"/>The hard, incurable, and cruel Stone,</l>
                  <l>Which wou'd make Heart, as hard as it, bemoan</l>
                  <l>Man's Miſery, here with the ſubt'leſt Stroke,</l>
                  <l>Like that of Thunder, ſhatter'd is, and broke.</l>
                  <l>The rooted Griefs all Parts begin to leave,</l>
                  <l>All Parts their priſtine Nimbleneſs receive.</l>
                  <l>You ſee the Countenance begin to clear,</l>
                  <l>The Hands are freſh, the Goddeſs Looks appear</l>
                  <l>In every Face; Ladies her Waters drink,</l>
                  <l>That they had drank her Beauty too, you'd think:</l>
                  <l>A freſh Complexion, and that greater Grace,</l>
                  <l>Brisk Chearfulneſs enlivens every Face.</l>
                  <l>Where Features are, it gives of Beauty more</l>
                  <l>Than Nature eve'n at Birth beſtow'd before.</l>
                  <l>Not only cures, but it does too improve,</l>
                  <l>Repairs Love's Object, and encreaſes Love.</l>
                  <l>The Heart, that is ſo great a Fountain too</l>
                  <l>Of Life, this ſaving Fountain does out do.</l>
                  <l>From that, bare Life, and ſickly; from this, we</l>
                  <l>Of Health and Life receive Security.</l>
                  <l>Not only cleanſing; rather we ſhou'd call</l>
                  <l>This Water the <hi>Chalybeat Cordial.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>Venus</hi> thus and <hi>Mars</hi> together bleſs,</l>
                  <l>All noiſome Vapours both of 'em ſuppreſs</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:100354:43"/>All <hi>Apoplectick</hi> Fumes. What can we dread,</l>
                  <l>When two ſuch Luminaries clear the Head?</l>
                  <l>Other great Medi'cines cure, but each apart:</l>
                  <l>This the whole Man; the Liver, Head, the Heart,</l>
                  <l>And every Limb renews with God-like Art:</l>
                  <l>Relieves the almoſt ſtupified Brain,</l>
                  <l>Works off its Clouds, and gives it Life again.</l>
                  <l>Quickens with Spirits the quite-blunted Wit,</l>
                  <l>With new-enabled Fancy helpeth it.</l>
                  <l>Wit that before abſconded, now 's not ſhye,</l>
                  <l>Shines in the Look, and ſparkles through the Eye,</l>
                  <l>With quick Look ſhews reſtored Memory.</l>
                  <l>The Scholar ſtruggling feels recover'd Brain,</l>
                  <l>Imbelliſh'd Fancy ſpeaks ſtrong Lines again,</l>
                  <l>Thinks freely of all Objects, fills with Senſe,</l>
                  <l>And uſes his old native Eloquence.</l>
                  <l>Choak'd Lungs reſpire, now firſt we feel, 'tis true,</l>
                  <l>That we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are alive: we feel our ſelves all new.</l>
                  <l>Our Souls in ſickly Bodies tir'd ſo long,</l>
                  <l>Tranſinigrate here into the ſound and ſtrong.</l>
                  <l>As if with <hi>Lethe</hi> waſh'd, no more they fret</l>
                  <l>At Sorrows paſt, but all their Pains forget.</l>
                  <l>Leaving the gloomy Shades then from the fair</l>
                  <l>Fountain, they go into the opener Air;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:100354:43"/>There dwell all day in green and pleaſant Fields</l>
                  <l>(Such Places too this new <hi>Elyſium</hi> yields)</l>
                  <l>At perfect Eaſe. In this ſweet Place they walk,</l>
                  <l>In that they dance, by the Wood-ſide they talk,</l>
                  <l>Some excellent Poet yonder makes his Verſe,</l>
                  <l>Another here takes pleaſure to reherſe;</l>
                  <l>The Wits that hear, admire; all Wits delight,</l>
                  <l>Theſe hear with Pleaſure, thoſe with Pleaſure write.</l>
                  <l>Here Friend meets his old Friend, the amo'rous Lad,</l>
                  <l>Fond Lover, finds his Miſtreſs, and is glad.</l>
                  <l>Under that Oak contemplating we ſee</l>
                  <l>Some great Improver of Philoſophy.</l>
                  <l>A little farther, by that Maple ſits</l>
                  <l>Yet harder Student ſtraining of his Wits;</l>
                  <l>Studying the Globe, the Elements and Plants;</l>
                  <l>And caſting up what our ſhort Knowledge wants.</l>
                  <l>Near theſe, great Heroes, of a higher Fate,</l>
                  <l>Settle in Solitude Affairs of State,</l>
                  <l>Having laid down the Burden of ill Health,</l>
                  <l>Now with Delight ſupport the Commonwealth.</l>
                  <l>Free from that Throng of Clients, and alone,</l>
                  <l>Their Time and Health here firſt can call their own.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:100354:44"/>
                     <hi>Atlas's</hi> of the Land, much better bear</l>
                  <l>The burden here, than if at Court they were.</l>
                  <l>Not far from theſe, but in more gloomy walk,</l>
                  <l>Grave Citizens, gravely delighted, talk</l>
                  <l>Of their own little Commonwealth at home,</l>
                  <l>How they to helm of Merchandiſe may come.</l>
                  <l>In all conditions each one to his mind</l>
                  <l>Does here the pleaſure he affecteth find.</l>
                  <l>The Ladies round the pleaſant Country fly,</l>
                  <l>As if they had kind of Ubiquity.</l>
                  <l>No pleaſant place, but the gay Troop are there,</l>
                  <l>Daily they meet, and they meet every where.</l>
                  <l>The Muſick follows 'em; as Angels do,</l>
                  <l>They carry Heaven about with 'em too;</l>
                  <l>At the appointed place they meet a train</l>
                  <l>Of Glorious Gallants ready on the plain,</l>
                  <l>And ſo well dreſs'd appear, Jewels and they</l>
                  <l>Out-ſmile the Meadows and vye with the day.</l>
                  <l>In graceful poſtures Men the Ladies meet,</l>
                  <l>In ſolemn dance advance their nimble feet,</l>
                  <l>To exact ſteps; with all the grace that can</l>
                  <l>On Earth belong to the Corporeal Man.</l>
                  <l>Some Banquet hard by theſe, one on the Lute</l>
                  <l>Plays a choice Tune, whilſt all admire, all mute.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:100354:44"/>Some Lady with rare Voice a well-ſet Song</l>
                  <l>Sings to the Reſt, and raviſhes the Throng.</l>
                  <l>"A Heave'n on Earth; cou'd ſuch ſmall paſtime ſill</l>
                  <l>"Man's mighty mind; and cou'd it be ſo ſtill.</l>
                  <l>Nor now dear bought, though precious time, be price</l>
                  <l>Once in a Year of ſuch a Paradiſe.</l>
                  <l>Pity that every Winter ſhou'd deface</l>
                  <l>That which at Summer is ſo ſweet a place.</l>
                  <l>Pity juſt pleaſure ſhou'd no longer hold</l>
                  <l>Than Summers heat, and with the Year grow cold.</l>
                  <l>The ſober Man might here at Winter be,</l>
                  <l>The Wit and Scholar wou'd be then more free.</l>
                  <l>The Air as well as Water does revive,</l>
                  <l>This makes us live, and that keeps us alive.</l>
                  <l>Nor cou'd God, that ſaves thus by Water 'have meant</l>
                  <l>T' aſſiſt us leſs with higher Element.</l>
                  <l>Great Earth, concern'd in both, by ſteel impowers</l>
                  <l>Water to Cure; the Air, with Herbs and Flowers.</l>
                  <l>The Soyl as fertile as can well be ſweet,</l>
                  <l>As much invites us to dwell there, as meet.</l>
                  <l>The ground is warm, and it is ſhelter'd ſo,</l>
                  <l>That all things there, if 'twere manur'd, might grow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:100354:45"/>Here choiceſt Flowe'rs, and there the pleaſant Vine</l>
                  <l>The Soil wou'd yield us; though not rich, yet fine,</l>
                  <l>If once improv'd, this wholeſome place wou'd be,</l>
                  <l>Rudeneſs adorn'd might riſe to Rarity.</l>
                  <l>It wants but Soil, which Company would bring:</l>
                  <l>Had it but Subjects, it might pleaſe a King.</l>
                  <l>The pleaſant Bottom, dry and ſandy ground,</l>
                  <l>Lies ſhelter'd with ſmall rocky Riſings round.</l>
                  <l>Some ſteeper, ſome of eaſier Aſcent:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe, with the pleaſant Soil to give, were meant,</l>
                  <l>Theſe to facilitate Divertiſement.</l>
                  <l>Tops of the Rocks are hardly to be ſeen,</l>
                  <l>But all with Heath are cover'd, or all Green.</l>
                  <l>Some diſtance off, all ſorts of Trees there are,</l>
                  <l>Better ſo plac'd than if they nearer were,</l>
                  <l>By Nature's great Contrivance, not to hide</l>
                  <l>The pleaſantneſs a Heath has in being wide.</l>
                  <l>The Heath, though on its Surface little grow,</l>
                  <l>For Uſe, yet it has Storehouſes below,</l>
                  <l>By Nature fill'd: Materials of its own</l>
                  <l>To build a City; Iron, Steel, and Stone;</l>
                  <l>Too much Sand to be uſeleſs, there is hill'd,</l>
                  <l>And heap'd by Nature, all given us to build.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:100354:45"/>Take hence an <hi>Omen</hi> then: Nature's deſign</l>
                  <l>Sure muſt have been in time to make it fine.</l>
                  <l>Though now but ſcatter'd place, yet we may know</l>
                  <l>What 'tis to be, we ſee 'tis like to grow;</l>
                  <l>Already future Cities <hi>Embryo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The pretty Walk, the Crowd, the ſplendid ſtreet</l>
                  <l>Of Shops above, the Market Folks that meet,</l>
                  <l>The frequent People, Gentry mixt-with Clown,</l>
                  <l>Makes up a <hi>ſomething,</hi> ſomething like a Town.</l>
                  <l>That 'tis no more built yet, to the ſweet place</l>
                  <l>Can be no ſhame; to us is more diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Who hitherto to ſo benefick Spring</l>
                  <l>Have made no better Free-will-Offering.</l>
                  <l>Not all new Towns for Wealth, but ſome for Fame</l>
                  <l>Are built, or Health; ſome to preſerve a Name.</l>
                  <l>Let theſe bright Springs ſome brighter name pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</l>
                  <l>Than dirty <hi>Tunbridge;</hi> better they deſerve.</l>
                  <l>For Health, the Miracles which here are done</l>
                  <l>By Air and Water, methinks ſhould have won</l>
                  <l>The cur'd in Gratitude; the ſick at leaſt</l>
                  <l>Shou'd be convinc'd by their own Intereſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:100354:46"/>To finiſh theſe beginnings of a Town,</l>
                  <l>Which thus unbuilt bring ſuch a concourſe down.</l>
                  <l>Theſe Fundamentals, <hi>London,</hi> with thee ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>Already which keeps moſt of thine alive.</l>
                  <l>The place thus urges thee, where can thy Wealth</l>
                  <l>Be better ſpent, than where 't's repay'd with Health?</l>
                  <l>Of all thy Principals, (though here be leaſt)</l>
                  <l>'Twoud pay yet the beſt ſort of Intereſt.</l>
                  <l>From Vulture's flying the' Founder of great <hi>Rome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conceiv'd firſt hopes of what was then to come.</l>
                  <l>The place was mark'd to <hi>'Aeneas</hi> by white Swine,</l>
                  <l>A proſperous Colour, but no hopeful Sign.</l>
                  <l>Who wou'd have thought, that ruiner of ground</l>
                  <l>Shou'd ſhow, where Gods ſtill-ſtanding <hi>Rome</hi> wou'd found?</l>
                  <l>We here have better, whiter Signs in ſight,</l>
                  <l>The faireſt proſpect of a fair delight.</l>
                  <l>No rav'nous Vulture invites, nor Swiniſh wealth,</l>
                  <l>Nor brutiſh pleaſure, but thou, candid Health:</l>
                  <l>And all thoſe rural paſtimes which agree</l>
                  <l>With Innocence and Ingenuity.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:100354:46"/>Nor does Heaven now its Will by Brutes declare,</l>
                  <l>Or flying Vultures: Elements here are</l>
                  <l>Both cauſe and Omens of our future bliſs:</l>
                  <l>Air with the Water does prognoſtick this.</l>
                  <l>Earth too concurrs; Three of the Four agree</l>
                  <l>T' invite us with auſpicious Augury.</l>
                  <l>The Springs that cauſe our Health, do Health fore tell,</l>
                  <l>The Air gives Hopes we may continue well.</l>
                  <l>The Earth, though no ſuch fertile Crops it give,</l>
                  <l>Yet by its Barrenneſs helps us to live,</l>
                  <l>Perfumes and purifies the Air we breath,</l>
                  <l>The Soil, though barren, fragrant is beneath.</l>
                  <l>Where Nature three parts of her Fabrick draws</l>
                  <l>Into' one efficient conglobated Cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Of what her Wiſdom here means to beſtow,</l>
                  <l>Fore-ſhews the' Effects in Cauſes whence they flow.</l>
                  <l>From ſo great Omens, ſure we may divine;</l>
                  <l>Predict Felicity from greateſt Sign.</l>
                  <l>Our future Health, Experience does foretell:</l>
                  <l>Where oft we have been, we may ſtill be, well;</l>
                  <l>We as great Omens of our Pleaſure might</l>
                  <l>Take from what is, to what will be, Delight.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:100354:47"/>A Place where City' and Court divert as well</l>
                  <l>As any where; where Poet yet might dwell</l>
                  <l>On a <hi>Parnaſs;</hi> near as Divine a Well,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Helicon;</hi> and in a Muſe's Oell. —</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Acer</hi> ſpake.</l>
                  <l>You 'have ſo with Wit improv'd this barren Ground,</l>
                  <l>The Town, which you there propheſie, you found:</l>
                  <l>With Fancy' embelliſh'd, and with Verſe adorn'd,</l>
                  <l>For th' Muſes ſake it can no more be ſcorn'd.</l>
                  <l>What-e'er that <hi>Something</hi> be, thou 'ſt made it ſeem</l>
                  <l>Already ſomething worthy of Eſteem.</l>
                  <l>In Mens Opinion the ſmall place will grow,</l>
                  <l>And ſoon come to be more than <hi>Embryo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nature's Example moves; the Muſes wooe,</l>
                  <l>Fortune's oblig'd to be propitious too,</l>
                  <l>What may n't that Goddeſs, when ſo courted do?</l>
                  <l>Cities, at firſt, they ſay, from Poets came,</l>
                  <l>Why may n't this <hi>Helicon</hi> do here the ſame,</l>
                  <l>And thou raiſe Walls by raiſing of their Fame?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:100354:47"/>
                  <speaker>Metell.</speaker>
                  <l>We all then thank him briefly, let him know</l>
                  <l>How much to him this Place and Fountain owe.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Laelius,</hi> who was to have next Debate</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Acer,</hi> we entreated to Tranſlate</l>
                  <l>Th' Fourth Book of <hi>Virgil</hi> firſt: then he ſhou'd be,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt <hi>Acer,</hi> Advocate for Liberty.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:100354:48"/>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:100354:48"/>
            <head>THE Third Dialogue. OF Tranſlation.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Metell.</speaker>
               <l>WE met again, when with Poetick Rage</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acer</hi> incens'd, exclaim'd againſt the Age;</l>
               <l>Said ſome of our new Poets had of late</l>
               <l>Set up a lazie Faſhion to Tranſlate.</l>
               <l>Speak Authours how they pleaſe, and if they call</l>
               <l>Stuff they make Paraphraſe; that anſwers all.</l>
               <l>Pedantick Verſe; effeminately ſmooth,</l>
               <l>Rack'd through all little Rules of Art to ſooth.</l>
               <l>The ſoft'ned Age induſtriouſly compile,</l>
               <l>Maim Wit, and cripple Fancy all the while.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:100354:49"/>A Licence far beyond <hi>Poetick</hi> Uſe,</l>
               <l>Not to Tranſlate old Authours, but abuſe</l>
               <l>The Wit of <hi>Romans;</hi> and their lofty Senſe</l>
               <l>Degrade into new Poem made from thence,</l>
               <l>Diſguiſe old <hi>Rome</hi> in our New Eloquence.</l>
            </sp>
            <l>
               <hi>Aeſculape</hi> ſaid he was of the ſame mind,</l>
            <l>And thought it fit Wits ſhou'd be more confin'd</l>
            <l>To Authour's Senſe, and to their Periods too,</l>
            <l>Muſt leave out nothing; every Senſe muſt do.</l>
            <l>And though they cannot render Verſe for Verſe,</l>
            <l>Yet every Period's Senſe they muſt reherſe.</l>
            <sp>
               <stage>Then <hi>Curio</hi> ſpake.</stage>
               <l>O do not reprehend</l>
               <l>Too ſharply, <hi>Acer,</hi> Speak more like a Friend:</l>
               <l>Time and Experience many Faults may mend.</l>
               <l>Though Vertue' in Stoick, yet of modern Crimes</l>
               <l>It is the worſt to contradict the Times.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Aeſculape</hi> then.</stage>
               <l>It cannot be amiſs</l>
               <l>That we, <hi>Metellus,</hi> yet inculcate this</l>
               <l>To modiſh <hi>Laelius,</hi> that he do it ſo,</l>
               <l>The Draught may <hi>Virgil</hi> more than <hi>Laelius</hi> ſhow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:100354:49"/>
               <speaker>Metell.</speaker>
               <l>We all then bid tranſlate it the old way,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>A-la-mode,</hi> but like
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Sandys</hi>'s <hi>Metamorphoſis,</hi> and <hi>May</hi>'s <hi>Lucan.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>George Sandys</hi> or <hi>May;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shew <hi>Virgil</hi>'s every Period: not ſteal Senſe,</l>
               <l>To make up a new-faſhion'd Poem thence,</l>
               <l>In our New Tongue, ſpeak his old Eloquence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lael.</speaker>
               <l>But <hi>Laelius</hi> bowing. Too much ye injoin,</l>
               <l>O Friends, ſaid he, to ſuch a Wit as mine,</l>
               <l>To render truly' in Verſe, Verſe ſo Divine.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> ſpeech for higheſt things deſign'd,</l>
               <l>Can ſcarce be to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue confin'd;</l>
               <l>No modern Language now-a-days can bear</l>
               <l>So high a Sea as <hi>Virgil</hi> raiſes here:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="bottom">In <hi>Virgil</hi>'s Fourth Book.</note> ſhipwrack there.</l>
               <l>Our moſt applauded
<note n="*" place="bottom">Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poets at home.</note> Poets, though they touch</l>
               <l>Here with their Pencils, yet han't drawn us much:</l>
               <l>And thoſe who on this Book thought fit to ſpend</l>
               <l>Some of their Pains, nor yet begin 't, nor end.</l>
               <l>But ſince in ſomething they have ſhewn the way,</l>
               <l>And ye command, I'll venture to obey;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:100354:50"/>Hope to ſpeak <hi>Virgil,</hi> and ſpeak <hi>Engliſh</hi> too,</l>
               <l>May not be more than 's poſſible to do.</l>
               <l>But Wits, remember, 'his nobler <hi>Latin</hi> Clothes</l>
               <l>He now puts off, ours wo'n't adorn like thoſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Metell.</speaker>
               <l>So he took leave; We left him to his pain</l>
               <l>For fourteen Days, then all return again;</l>
               <l>When <hi>Laelius</hi> with an anſwerable Meen,</l>
               <l>Grief and Compaſſion, eminently ſeen</l>
               <l>Both in his Looks, read his <hi>Deſerted Queen.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Laelius <hi>reads the following Tranſlation.</hi>
            </stage>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="excerpt">
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:100354:50"/>
                        <head>THE FOURTH BOOK OF VIRGIL In <hi>ENGLISH.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head type="sub">THE Deſerted Queen.</head>
                        <argument>
                           <head>The ARGUMENT.</head>
                           <p>Virgil <hi>in his firſt Book of</hi> Aeneids <hi>deſcribes</hi> Aeneas <hi>his Voyage by Sea, from loſt</hi> Troy <hi>to</hi> Carthage, <hi>and his Reception there; where, after a great Supper,</hi> Dido <hi>deſiring him, he elegantly relates the Deſtruction of</hi> Troy, <hi>and then his Voyage from</hi> Troy <hi>to</hi> Carthage; <hi>which Relations are the Subject of</hi> Virgil'<hi>s Second and Third Book. The Queen, whilſt he is telling his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, falls in Love with him. That Love of</hi> Dido'<hi>s is the Subject of this Fourth</hi> Aeneid.</p>
                        </argument>
                        <lg>
                           <pb n="86" facs="tcp:100354:51"/>
                           <l>MEan while the Queen, inflam'd with great deſire,</l>
                           <l>Full of Love-cares, burns with a ſecret Fire,</l>
                           <l>Fond of her wound, indulges the ſweet pains:</l>
                           <l>The ſecret grief is nouriſh'd in her Veins.</l>
                           <l>His Countrey's worth, his looks and words bereave</l>
                           <l>Her of her Reſt, and great Impreſſion leave.</l>
                           <l>Soon as the Morning brake, and the light ſhin'd,</l>
                           <l>Thus to her Siſter ſhe diſclos'd her mind.</l>
                           <l>O Siſter! what ſad Dreams have I? they fright</l>
                           <l>And keep me waking almoſt all the night.</l>
                           <l>What <hi>Hero</hi>'s this we have? How he's been bleſt?</l>
                           <l>What meen he has? How 'invincible a Breaſt?</l>
                           <l>'Twixt him and Deities there's little Odds,</l>
                           <l>Truly 'I believe he's of the Race of Gods.</l>
                           <l>Baſe minds ſtill ſhew ſome fear; How boldly he</l>
                           <l>(Toſs'd with what Fates?) has broke through miſery?</l>
                           <l>What Wars he tells?—</l>
                           <l>O had I not reſolv'd to love no more,</l>
                           <l>Nor ever <hi>Hymen</hi>'s Power to implore,</l>
                           <l>Bereav'd of my <hi>Sichaeus,</hi> that is dead;</l>
                           <l>Did I not hate all Thoughts of Marriage-Bed,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="87" facs="tcp:100354:51"/>I might perhaps have yielded to this one,</l>
                           <l>This only fault, and one Love more might own.</l>
                           <l>Yet, Deareſt Siſter! I muſt needs confeſs</l>
                           <l>Since my <hi>Sichaeus</hi> dy'd, no object leſs</l>
                           <l>Than ſuch a Hero cou'd e'er move my mind,</l>
                           <l>But now, again, Oh! my firſt Flames I find.</l>
                           <l>Yet may the Earth firſt ſwallow me; may 'I go</l>
                           <l>Struck with a Thunderbolt to ſhades below,</l>
                           <l>Before or Man, or any thing ſhou'd draw</l>
                           <l>Me, Modeſty, to violate thy Law.</l>
                           <l>No, thou, whoſe Fortune firſt it was to have</l>
                           <l>My Love, ſhalt keep it, keep it in thy Grave.</l>
                           <l>Thus ſpake the Queen, nor at theſe words forbears,</l>
                           <l>To bath her Boſom with a ſhowre of Tears.</l>
                           <l>Her Siſter anſwer'd; Dearer than the light,</l>
                           <l>Whilſt <hi>Venus</hi> Bleſſings do ſo much invite,</l>
                           <l>Siſter, will you here ſolitary ſpend</l>
                           <l>Your Youth in ſorrow thus to your lives end?</l>
                           <l>By ſuch a Husband, and ſuch hopes of Son,</l>
                           <l>As you have now, you ſhou'd methinks be won.</l>
                           <l>Alas! d' you think Ghoſts of the buried care</l>
                           <l>What we do here, or what our Actions are?</l>
                           <l>Suppoſe you did not yield to ſome before</l>
                           <l>You cou'd not like, muſt you ne'er marry more?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="88" facs="tcp:100354:52"/>Becauſe <hi>Iarbas</hi> and ſuch, did not take,</l>
                           <l>Therefore muſt you this Hero too forſake?</l>
                           <l>The Man you like deny? One ſo above</l>
                           <l>Thoſe wild <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and oppoſe ſweet Love?</l>
                           <l>'Pray think but where you are, and on what ground</l>
                           <l>Your City ſtands, and who your Realm ſurround?</l>
                           <l>On this ſide of you, the <hi>Getulians</hi> lye,</l>
                           <l>Unconquer'd Men; on that, you have hard by</l>
                           <l>The wild <hi>Numidians,</hi> who live moſt by Theft,</l>
                           <l>And Robberies. Yonder's a Land that's left,</l>
                           <l>Not habitable for the ſcorching heat;</l>
                           <l>Of Savage Beaſts the formidable Seat.</l>
                           <l>A little farther the <hi>Barcaeans</hi> live,</l>
                           <l>A Warlike Nation; each of theſe may give</l>
                           <l>You trouble 'enough, but none will e'er relieve.</l>
                           <l>Nor have you cleared with <hi>Pigmalion</hi> yet</l>
                           <l>Old ſcores, who may pretend ſtill to his debt,</l>
                           <l>And to Revenge.</l>
                           <l>Th' Immortal Gods and <hi>Juno</hi> muſt have meant</l>
                           <l>A match ſure with us, when they wiſely ſent.</l>
                           <l>Theſe Warlike <hi>Trojans</hi> to 'our unſetled ſtate,</l>
                           <l>What cou'd they come for, but to urge our Fate?</l>
                           <l>And if ſuch City now be rais'd by thee,</l>
                           <l>Siſter, alone; how glorious will it be,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="89" facs="tcp:100354:52"/>When <hi>Trojan</hi> Arms thou by this match ſhalt join,</l>
                           <l>And <hi>Trojan</hi> glory too unite with thine?</l>
                           <l>Go, pray the Gods to pardon you, and bleſs</l>
                           <l>Your good Intentions, then entreat your Gueſts</l>
                           <l>To ſtay a while yet, (there is reaſon enough)</l>
                           <l>Whilſt Winds are boyſterous, and whilſt Seas are rough.</l>
                           <l>When ſhe'd ſpoke thus, the Queen was in a flame,</l>
                           <l>Conceiv'd ſuch hopes, ſh' had little care of ſhame.</l>
                           <l>They go before the Images, obey</l>
                           <l>The Siſter's Counſel, at the Altars pray.</l>
                           <l>To <hi>Ceres, Phoebus,</hi> and too <hi>Bacchus</hi> Sheep</l>
                           <l>They kill; and a great Holiday they keep</l>
                           <l>Unto the God of Liberty; but move</l>
                           <l>'Bove all the
<note n="*" place="margin">Juno.</note> Goddeſs of all Marriage-Love</l>
                           <l>Beautiful <hi>Dido</hi> moſt devoutly ſtands</l>
                           <l>Before the Altar, with Cup in her hands</l>
                           <l>Of Wine, ſhe pow'rs betwixt the white Cows Horns,</l>
                           <l>Then ſtately walking, ſhe the place adorns,</l>
                           <l>Before the Images, and then ſhe brings</l>
                           <l>And offers up ſome other coſtly things.</l>
                           <l>With the wiſe Augur greedily ſhe pryes</l>
                           <l>Into the Intrails of the Beaſt that dies.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="90" facs="tcp:100354:53"/>O, what to ſuch Curioſity could move?</l>
                           <l>How vain, alas! is Augury in Love?</l>
                           <l>Ah, what can Temple, what can Image do;</l>
                           <l>Or Praye'rs, when Women are reſolv'd to wooe?</l>
                           <l>When the ſoft Flames of Love in Heart are found</l>
                           <l>Within, inflaming of the hidden Wound:</l>
                           <l>Unhappy <hi>Dido</hi> ſmitten, burning ſo,</l>
                           <l>Like one that 's mad doth 'bout the City go,</l>
                           <l>Juſt as a Hind which Shepherd who has ſhot</l>
                           <l>Knows not h' has hit, nor kill'd upon the Spot;</l>
                           <l>Gall'd with the Dart, runs all about the Wood,</l>
                           <l>The Foreſt, Fields, where nothing does her good:</l>
                           <l>Sometimes near the known Paths, and ſometimes wide,</l>
                           <l>Still with the deadly Arrow in her ſide:</l>
                           <l>So does the Queen; Sometimes upon the Walls</l>
                           <l>She walks the Heroe; ſuddenly ſhe calls</l>
                           <l>Him down again, and all her Riches ſhows;</l>
                           <l>Abroad with him to ſee the City goes:</l>
                           <l>Begins to ſpeak, but then breaks off again,</l>
                           <l>All things ſhe does, but Love, ſhe does with Pain.</l>
                           <l>The ſelf-ſame Day a Banquet ſhe will have,</l>
                           <l>There but to hear his great Exploits does crave;</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="91" facs="tcp:100354:53"/>She hears, and is tranſported with his Praiſe;</l>
                           <l>Hangs on his Lips, admiring all he ſays.</l>
                           <l>Soon as ſhe ſees he and his Friends are gone,</l>
                           <l>And the dark Night apace is coming on,</l>
                           <l>Muſing ſhe ſits in the forſaken Room,</l>
                           <l>Pleas'd with the Thought, That he again may come;</l>
                           <l>Sits on the Bed, where they ſo lately were,</l>
                           <l>And wiſhes ſtill the brave <hi>Aeneas</hi> there.</l>
                           <l>She hears him abſent, and ſhe ſees him too:</l>
                           <l>(O what Perſwaſion won't Love bring us to?)</l>
                           <l>His little Son ſhe to her Lap does take,</l>
                           <l>And hugs <hi>Aſcanius</hi> for his Father's ſake.</l>
                           <l>With the' Heroe quite tak'n up, no Work goes on,</l>
                           <l>All thought of finiſhing the City's gone;</l>
                           <l>No Towers riſe, nor Bulwarks now of War:</l>
                           <l>Nor work they at the Haven there, nor are</l>
                           <l>The Youth c'er train'd now under ſtrict Command:</l>
                           <l>The great Deſigns are all quite at a ſtand.</l>
                           <l>Which ſoon as Heaven's Queen had underſtood,</l>
                           <l>Saw Fame in Fury cou'd do little good,</l>
                           <l>All Senſe of Honour, Reputation gone,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Venus</hi> at laſt then thus ſhe fell upon.</l>
                           <l>Great Spoils indeed, a mighty laſting Name</l>
                           <l>You and your Son will get, and a great Fame;</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="92" facs="tcp:100354:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>If one poor miſerable Woman is</l>
                           <l>Vanquiſh'd by the' Craft of two ſuch Deities.</l>
                           <l>I well enough perceive what 'tis you fear,</l>
                           <l>How jealous you of me at <hi>Carthage</hi> are,</l>
                           <l>Of my Powe'r there. But what needs ſuch Diſpute?</l>
                           <l>Your Intereſt with mine, I hope, may ſute.</l>
                           <l>Let's make a laſting Peace, and a Match too,</l>
                           <l>You 'have done all you can ever hope to doe.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Dio</hi> 's on fire; your Fury 'has pierc'd the Bone,</l>
                           <l>Come let us make then theſe two Nations one,</l>
                           <l>And jointly rule. Let <hi>Dido,</hi> if ſhe's won</l>
                           <l>With all her Dowry, have your <hi>Trojan</hi> Son.</l>
                           <l>But <hi>Venus,</hi> well perceiving what ſhe thought,</l>
                           <l>That ſo the' <hi>Italian</hi> Empire might be brought</l>
                           <l>To <hi>Carthage</hi> too, with great <hi>Aeneas</hi> Fate;</l>
                           <l>Reply'd thus: Who 'is ſo mad, as to debate</l>
                           <l>All this with you? Who, think you, wou'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend</l>
                           <l>In War with <hi>Juno?</hi> Rather make an end.</l>
                           <l>Provided Fortune follow what you ſay;</l>
                           <l>And what you wou'd do, <hi>Jove</hi> will grant you may.</l>
                           <l>But who can tell whe'ther that dear Son of mine,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Jove</hi> does intend, ſhou'd with his, <hi>Tyrians</hi> join;</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="93" facs="tcp:100354:54"/>Whether thoſe Nations Mixture he wou'd like,</l>
                           <l>Or give 'em leave a laſting League to ſtrike.</l>
                           <l>You are his Queen, you beſt may know his Mind;</l>
                           <l>Begin, I'll ſecond you. That I will find,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Juno</hi> reply'd. But that which for your Son,</l>
                           <l>And <hi>Dido</hi> is at preſent to be done,</l>
                           <l>How to contrive, but hearken, and I'll ſhow.</l>
                           <l>Poor <hi>Dido</hi> with <hi>Aeneas</hi> means to go</l>
                           <l>To hunt to morrow: as ſoon as his Rays</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Titan</hi> on the enlighten'd Earth diſplays.</l>
                           <l>Whilſt they beſet the Wood, and whilſt the Court</l>
                           <l>Are all engag'd, and eager on their Sport,</l>
                           <l>I'll rain and hail, and cover all with Night,</l>
                           <l>With Thunder then the Company ſo fright,</l>
                           <l>I'll make 'em fly.</l>
                           <l>Then <hi>Dido</hi> and <hi>Aeneas</hi> both ſhall come</l>
                           <l>To the ſame Cave, I'll there give 'em their Doom,</l>
                           <l>And marry 'em, if I have your Conſent.</l>
                           <l>But <hi>Venus</hi> quickly finding what ſhe meant,</l>
                           <l>Smil'd at her Craft, but wou'd not yet diſſent.</l>
                           <l>Soon as 'twas Day, the brisk Youth of the Court</l>
                           <l>All at the Gate were ready for the Sport.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="94" facs="tcp:100354:55"/>With Toyles, Nets, Spears, and a great ſtrength of Hound;</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Maſſilian</hi> Horſe too prancing on the Ground:</l>
                           <l>The <hi>Tyrian</hi> Nobles all attend the Queen,</l>
                           <l>Till ſhe come forth. The' Horſe at the Door is ſeen</l>
                           <l>In Gold and Purple, on which ſhe 's to ſit,</l>
                           <l>Trampling the Ground, and champing on the Bit.</l>
                           <l>The Queen comes forth with a great Train, at laſt,</l>
                           <l>In <hi>Tyrian</hi> Habit, which Embroidery grac'd.</l>
                           <l>Her Quiver Gold; Gold her fair Hair did hold,</l>
                           <l>The Button of her Veſtment too was Gold.</l>
                           <l>The <hi>Trojans</hi> with their brisk <hi>Iulus</hi> go:</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aeneas</hi> above all Men you might know,</l>
                           <l>When he came up his Countrymen to join,</l>
                           <l>He in his Meen had ſo much of Divine.</l>
                           <l>Juſt as the God <hi>Apollo</hi> when he goes</l>
                           <l>From <hi>Lycia</hi> to <hi>Delos</hi> where all thoſe</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cretes, Dryopes,</hi> and <hi>Agathyrſians</hi> ſound</l>
                           <l>Aloud his Praiſe, appears his Forehead bound,</l>
                           <l>On <hi>Cynthus</hi> Hill, with Gold and nobler Bays,</l>
                           <l>Reſplendent, glorious, and in all his Rays.</l>
                           <l>As he is ſeen, whilſt all thoſe Nations ſing,</l>
                           <l>Whilſt briskly walking, all his Arrows ring;</l>
                           <l>Juſt in ſuch Splendour went the <hi>Trojan</hi> King.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="95" facs="tcp:100354:55"/>But when the Hunters were got up the Hill,</l>
                           <l>Had beat the Woods; whilſt they were beating ſtill,</l>
                           <l>They ſaw firſt ſome wild Goats, ignoble Game,</l>
                           <l>Which skipping o'er the craggy Mountains came.</l>
                           <l>On the' other ſide came down a Herd of Deer;</l>
                           <l>Croſſing the Plain, the duſty Staggs appear:</l>
                           <l>But young <hi>Aſcanius</hi> in the Vale below</l>
                           <l>Sports, and the Mettle of his Horſe to ſhow,</l>
                           <l>Now theſe out-rides, and now thoſe wou'd out-go.</l>
                           <l>Aſpires to higher Sport, deſires more</l>
                           <l>Than Hart, to' encounter Lyon or wild Boar.</l>
                           <l>When, the Clouds murmu'ring, a fierce Storm aroſe,</l>
                           <l>Heaven drowns with Rain, and Hails a Showre of Blows.</l>
                           <l>New Rivers riſe from Top of eve'ry Hill;</l>
                           <l>Run down like Seas; The Vales begin to fill.</l>
                           <l>The <hi>Tyrians, Trojans,</hi> all to the' Tempeſt yield,</l>
                           <l>And fly half-drown'd or ſton'd out of the Field.</l>
                           <l>Some to one Cottage, ſome to' another fly,</l>
                           <l>Stand under Trees; ſome in dark Caves do lye.</l>
                           <l>Whilſt all diſperſe, all ſtrive themſelves to ſave,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Dido</hi> and <hi>Aeneas</hi> light on the ſame Cave.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="96" facs="tcp:100354:56"/>The trembling Earth gave an unlucky Sign</l>
                           <l>To the' wicked Act, and though great <hi>Juno</hi> join,</l>
                           <l>The Air yet thunde'ring then might well be thought</l>
                           <l>(It light'ning too) ill Omen to the Fault;</l>
                           <l>The Mountain-Nymphs howl out loud as they can;</l>
                           <l>That Day all <hi>Dido</hi>'s Miſery began.</l>
                           <l>Honour and Fame prevail with her no more</l>
                           <l>To hide her Fault, as ſhe had done before.</l>
                           <l>She calls it Marriage now, eaſily taught</l>
                           <l>By Love, alas, to colour ſo her Fault.</l>
                           <l>But Fame that ſuffers no ſuch Fault to lye</l>
                           <l>Long hid, through <hi>Libya</hi> with the News does fly.</l>
                           <l>"Fame, far the ſwifteſt Evil that we know,</l>
                           <l>"Going gets Strength, in ſtirring quickens ſo.</l>
                           <l>"Small firſt and fearful: then begins to try</l>
                           <l>"Her Strength in the' Air, and greater grows on high.</l>
                           <l>"She walks firſt upon Earth, then hides her Head</l>
                           <l>"Among the Clouds, as wide as Heaven ſpread.</l>
                           <l>"Offended with the Gods, the angry Earth,</l>
                           <l>"Gave to this monſtrous Goddeſs firſt her Birth.</l>
                           <l>"Siſter to <hi>Enceladus, Caeus,</hi> no leſs</l>
                           <l>"Than her huge Brothers, is the Gyanteſs.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="97" facs="tcp:100354:56"/>"Fleeteſt of Foot above all mortal things,</l>
                           <l>"Her Mother made her; gave her nimbleſt Wings.</l>
                           <l>"A horrid Monſter 'and huge; you may deſcry</l>
                           <l>"Under each Feather which ſhe has, an <hi>Eye.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"As many <hi>Mouths</hi> ſhe has, as many <hi>Ears,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"As many <hi>Tongues</hi> to tell the things ſhe hears.</l>
                           <l>"By night ſhe flies ſhrill through the Air, below</l>
                           <l>"As ſwiftly does, and always tatling, go.</l>
                           <l>"Sleeps not at all, ſhe watching ſits by day</l>
                           <l>"On noble Roofs, hears what the great ones ſay,</l>
                           <l>"Or on high Towers: and telling what is Right,</l>
                           <l>"Oftner what's Wrong, great Cities does affright.</l>
                           <l>"Gigling abroad, ſhe all this did unfold,</l>
                           <l>"As well what was not, as what was ſhe told.</l>
                           <l>"That great <hi>Aeneas,</hi> of the <hi>Trojan</hi> Race,</l>
                           <l>"Was come to <hi>Carthage; Dido</hi> did embrace</l>
                           <l>"Him as a Husband: That they both pretend</l>
                           <l>"The Winter all in Luxury to ſpend.</l>
                           <l>"So take'n up both with Love, the Queen here quite</l>
                           <l>"Neglects all Buſi'neſs; he his foreign Right.</l>
                           <l>"This Fame had ſpread where-ever Men reſort;</l>
                           <l>"At laſt ſhe came quite to <hi>Iarba</hi>'s Court,</l>
                           <l>"Incens'd that King.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="98" facs="tcp:100354:57"/>This high-born Prince was Son to mighty <hi>Jove,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>And got on raviſh'd <hi>Garamant</hi> his Love.</l>
                           <l>Within his Realm, he' a hundred Temples built,</l>
                           <l>And ſo much Blood of ſlaughter'd Beaſts had ſpilt</l>
                           <l>Daily to the' Earth enriching it, it ſoak'd,</l>
                           <l>Daily to <hi>Jove</hi> his hundred Altars ſmoak'd.</l>
                           <l>He Temples deck'd, preſerv'd the Sacred Fire,</l>
                           <l>And had done all his Father cou'd require.</l>
                           <l>Vext at the Rumour which ill Fame had brought,</l>
                           <l>And much inrag'd, thus he great <hi>Jove</hi> beſought:</l>
                           <l>"O powe'rful King! whilſt <hi>Mauritanian</hi> Lords</l>
                           <l>"Are feaſting to thy Honour at their Boards;</l>
                           <l>"Doſt thou ſee this? Whilſt we adore thee thus,</l>
                           <l>"Doſt thou look down no better upon us?</l>
                           <l>"Or do we only fanſie that you reign,</l>
                           <l>"Father, and fear your Thunderbolts in vain?</l>
                           <l>"A rambling Woman ſome ill Fortune toſs'd</l>
                           <l>"Upon our Shore; here at a little Coſt</l>
                           <l>"She' has built a City: All their Lands to plow</l>
                           <l>"I gave. I gave 'em too their Laws, and now</l>
                           <l>"She ſcorns to marry ſuch a Man as me,</l>
                           <l>"Her only Lord <hi>Aeneas</hi> is to be.</l>
                           <l>"That fond, lewd <hi>Paris</hi> with 'his unmanly Train</l>
                           <l>"And butter'd Hair, the Lady does obtain.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="99" facs="tcp:100354:57"/>"Whilſt we, like Fools, make all theſe Altars flame,</l>
                           <l>"And idly here adore an empty Name.</l>
                           <l>"<hi>Jupiter</hi> ſaw him, and had heard him pray,</l>
                           <l>Holding the Altar (ſo much Prayers ſway)</l>
                           <l>He turn'd towa'rd <hi>Carthage,</hi> caſting of his Eye</l>
                           <l>On the fond Lovers, call'd for <hi>Mercury;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>And thus commands; "Make haſte, my Son, and goe</l>
                           <l>"Call the' Weſtern Wind, and ſlip to thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low;</l>
                           <l>"The <hi>Trojan Chief</hi> that out of a Reſpect</l>
                           <l>"To <hi>Dido,</hi> all his Fortune does neglect,</l>
                           <l>"Speak to, with ſpeed, from me; Tell him I ſee</l>
                           <l>"He's not the Man his Mother promis'd me.</l>
                           <l>"He was not at <hi>Troy</hi>'s Siege twice ſav'd for this,</l>
                           <l>"To aſpire only to a Lover's Bliſs.</l>
                           <l>"She told me, He would be a Man might ſway</l>
                           <l>"The <hi>Italian</hi> Sceptre, and prepare the way</l>
                           <l>"To the' Empire of the World. He that does ſpring</l>
                           <l>"From <hi>Teucer,</hi> ſhou'd be born to no leſs thing.</l>
                           <l>"But if the Glory of ſuch things as theſe</l>
                           <l>"Cannot prevail to draw him from his Eaſe:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="100" facs="tcp:100354:58"/>"Nor Senſe of Honour, nor Deſire of Praiſe</l>
                           <l>"Can make him ſtir, nor's Thoughts 'bove <hi>Carthage</hi> raiſe;</l>
                           <l>"Though <hi>Latium</hi> he forget, had rather wooe;</l>
                           <l>"He ſhou'd not grudge his Son <hi>Auſonia</hi> too.</l>
                           <l>"What does he mean? With what Hopes can he ſtay</l>
                           <l>"Thus among Foes, and never look that way?</l>
                           <l>"Bids him ſet Sail; that's all; <hi>Mercury,</hi> ſee</l>
                           <l>"You quickly give him this Command from me.</l>
                           <l>As ſoon as <hi>Jupiter</hi> had ſpoke, he goes,</l>
                           <l>And takes his Wings, tyes on his Golden Shooes,</l>
                           <l>With which he us'd to fly ov'er Sea and Land,</l>
                           <l>In all his Rays, his Wand too in his Hand,</l>
                           <l>With which he does ev'en Hell it ſelf controul,</l>
                           <l>Can call up, or can ſend down any Soul:</l>
                           <l>Can cauſe Sleep, or can hinder: thoſe that lye</l>
                           <l>In too long Pangs, with this can help to dye:</l>
                           <l>Condenſe or diſſipate the Clouds at eaſe;</l>
                           <l>Call and make uſe of any Wind he pleaſe.</l>
                           <l>Away he flies, and in his Flight the Top</l>
                           <l>Of <hi>Atlas</hi> ſees, and there makes his firſt ſtop.</l>
                           <l>That <hi>Atlas,</hi> which here holds its Head ſo high,</l>
                           <l>It's thought to bear the Burden of the Sky.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="101" facs="tcp:100354:58"/>This Mountain's clad in blackeſt Clouds: the Rain</l>
                           <l>And fierceſt Winds beat its hard Sides in vain.</l>
                           <l>Tall Pine-Trees cover 'his Head; his Shoulders, Snow:</l>
                           <l>His Beard's all Ice, from his Chin Rivers flow.</l>
                           <l>When bright <hi>Cyllenius</hi> had made here ſome ſtay,</l>
                           <l>Down towa'rds the Sea, through the' Air he ſlides away.</l>
                           <l>Juſt as that Bird of Prey, which we oft ſee</l>
                           <l>Low for a Fiſh, near Rocks and Shallows flye:</l>
                           <l>Juſt ſo, a way to <hi>Libya,</hi> through the Winds</l>
                           <l>'Twixt Heave'n and Earth, the ſwift <hi>Cyllenius</hi> finds.</l>
                           <l>Soon as he came to <hi>Carthage</hi> there he found</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aeneas</hi> buſie ſetting out of Ground</l>
                           <l>For Forts, and Towers which he meant to build,</l>
                           <l>And Town to be with both the Nations fill'd.</l>
                           <l>In <hi>Tyrian</hi> Mantle, which the Queen had ſent,</l>
                           <l>Richly with Gold embroider'd the' Hero went.</l>
                           <l>His Sword was ſet with <hi>Jaſpers,</hi> and inlaid</l>
                           <l>With fineſt Gold, to whom <hi>Cyllenius</hi> ſaid:</l>
                           <l>"You're founding here, uxorious Man, a Town</l>
                           <l>"That wo'n't be yours, nor will be your Renown;</l>
                           <l>"Forget, mean while, your Buſineſs, and that place</l>
                           <l>"That is deſign'd for you, and for your Race.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="102" facs="tcp:100354:59"/>"The King of Gods, that does with Smile or Frown</l>
                           <l>"Rule Heave'n and Earth, from Heaven ſends me down:</l>
                           <l>"Bids bring you theſe Commands: bids you obey;</l>
                           <l>"What's your Deſign? <hi>Jove</hi> wou'd know why you ſtay</l>
                           <l>"At <hi>Libya</hi> thus, and do n't the Fates obey?</l>
                           <l>"If Glory cannot to great Actions move</l>
                           <l>"You for your own ſake, at leaſt let the love</l>
                           <l>"You bear <hi>Iulus</hi> not be wholly vain,</l>
                           <l>"Give your Son leave in <hi>Italy</hi> to reign.</l>
                           <l>"From that great Glory which the Gods deſign</l>
                           <l>"You and your Race, O hinder not your Line.</l>
                           <l>Which when <hi>Cyllenius</hi> had ſaid, he quite</l>
                           <l>Vaniſhed at thoſe Words from mortal ſight.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aeneas</hi> at the Viſion ſenſeleſs ſtruck,</l>
                           <l>His Hair ſtood up, his Voice fail'd, his Words ſtuck.</l>
                           <l>Now he'd be gone, now the ſweet Place wou'd leave,</l>
                           <l>Him of vain Love the God's Commands bereave.</l>
                           <l>What can he do? He dares not tell the Queen:</l>
                           <l>Which way cou'd he begin? Or with what Meen?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="103" facs="tcp:100354:59"/>His Mind divides, he thinks now this, now that,</l>
                           <l>But cannot yet reſolve which way, nor what.</l>
                           <l>At laſt, whilſt with theſe Doubts he had no Reſt,</l>
                           <l>This Reſolution ſeem'd to him the beſt.</l>
                           <l>He calls <hi>Sergeſtus, Cloanth,</hi> and ſome more,</l>
                           <l>And bids 'em get their Men unto the Shore,</l>
                           <l>Provide the Fleet, and there be ready all,</l>
                           <l>But keep all ſecret; till their Leader call.</l>
                           <l>Sometime before the thing cou'd take effect,</l>
                           <l>Before the Queen cou'd have cauſe to ſuſpect,</l>
                           <l>To open 'it fairly, he'd try eve'ry way;</l>
                           <l>At ſofteſt times the ſofteſt things wou'd ſay.</l>
                           <l>Mean while the <hi>Trojans</hi> his Commands obey.</l>
                           <l>The Queen perceiving, That they meant to go,</l>
                           <l>(For who, alas! can cheat a Lover ſo?)</l>
                           <l>Suſpecting more than ſhe had Cauſeto fear,</l>
                           <l>And fearing eve'ry thing that ſhe cou'd hear;</l>
                           <l>Like Woman frantick, runs about, and falls</l>
                           <l>Into worſe Madneſs than at Bacchanals</l>
                           <l>A <hi>Thyas</hi> does.</l>
                           <l>At laſt <hi>Aeneas</hi> haſting to be gone,</l>
                           <l>She thus in higheſt Paſſion falls upon:</l>
                           <l>"And cou'd you think, perfidious Man, to hide</l>
                           <l>"So great a Wickedneſs? and wou'd you ſlide</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="104" facs="tcp:100354:60"/>"So ſilently too thus at laſt from me?</l>
                           <l>"Is all our Love ſo out of Memory?</l>
                           <l>"And ſha' n't that Promiſe, that Right Hand of thine</l>
                           <l>"So firmly, as I thought, once join'd to mine,</l>
                           <l>"Shall no Remembrance of our deareſt Love,</l>
                           <l>"Nor ſha' n't your dying <hi>Dido</hi> neither move?</l>
                           <l>"Can't all this make you ſtay, till Winter's gone?</l>
                           <l>"And but till favourabler Spring come on?</l>
                           <l>"Cruelleſt Man! though you ſought your own Land,</l>
                           <l>"Though ancient <hi>Troy</hi> in Splendour yet did ſtand,</l>
                           <l>"To' invite you home: yet who through ſo rough Seas</l>
                           <l>"Wou'd venture at Winter, with ſuch Winds as theſe?</l>
                           <l>"Or is it me you fly? By theſe ſad Tears,</l>
                           <l>"By that Right Hand of thine, by all my Fears,</l>
                           <l>"By' our Marriage, or if that Word ſpeak too much,</l>
                           <l>"By thoſe Beginnings of what ſhou'd be ſuch,</l>
                           <l>"I beg, if ever I deſerv'd of thee;</l>
                           <l>"If ever any thing did pleaſe in me,</l>
                           <l>"Pity my ruin'd Houſe; be n't ſo unkind,</l>
                           <l>"If Prayers can prevail, put off that Mind.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="105" facs="tcp:100354:60"/>"Me, for thy ſake, <hi>Numidian</hi> Princes hate,</l>
                           <l>"For thee, with the' <hi>Libyans</hi> I am at Debate.</l>
                           <l>"I 'have loſt the <hi>Tyrians</hi> Love only for thee,</l>
                           <l>"For thee alone I 'have loſt my Modeſty.</l>
                           <l>"O, and for thee I 'have loſt my former Fame,</l>
                           <l>"That had as high as Heaven rais'd my Name.</l>
                           <l>"But ſince I can to no more now pretend</l>
                           <l>"Than friendly Names, and ſince I thus muſt end,</l>
                           <l>"To whom, Oh, doſt thou leave thy dying Friend?</l>
                           <l>"O why do 'I ſtay? What till <hi>Pigmalion</hi> come</l>
                           <l>"Up to my Walls, and bring me my laſt Doom?</l>
                           <l>"Or till <hi>Iarbas</hi> Armies hither move,</l>
                           <l>"And take me to revenge his ſlighted Love?</l>
                           <l>"Hadſt thou but left me any thing of thee,</l>
                           <l>"A Son to have reviv'd thy Memory,</l>
                           <l>"A young <hi>Aeneas</hi> playing in my Hall,</l>
                           <l>"That had been thine, and might me Mother call,</l>
                           <l>"A Child that had but ſomething of thy Look,</l>
                           <l>"I had not been ſo totally forſook.</l>
                           <l>Though ſhe ſpake thus, <hi>Aeneas,</hi> as 't behov'd</l>
                           <l>One, <hi>Jove</hi> had call'd, never ſo much as mov'd</l>
                           <l>His fixed Eyes. But when he had ſuppreſt</l>
                           <l>What in him lay, the Trouble of his Breſt,</l>
                           <l>Briefly at laſt thus he himſelf expreſt:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="106" facs="tcp:100354:61"/>"I never ſhall deny, Queen, but to you</l>
                           <l>"From me, much you may reckon up is due;</l>
                           <l>"Nor ſhall I ever, whilſt this Soul's the ſame,</l>
                           <l>"Whilſt I'm my ſelf, forget <hi>Eliza</hi>'s Name.</l>
                           <l>"Thus much with Truth, I think may be reply'd,</l>
                           <l>"This Flight of mine I never meant to hide.</l>
                           <l>"(Do n't fanſie it) or ever did pretend</l>
                           <l>"To Husband's Rites, or to be more than Friend.</l>
                           <l>"If I might lead my Life as I deſire,</l>
                           <l>"<hi>Troy</hi> then would all, that I can do, require.</l>
                           <l>"Thither firſt I ſhou'd go, and there with Joy</l>
                           <l>"Repair the Ruines of my deareſt <hi>Troy.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"But now <hi>Apollo,</hi> whom I muſt obey,</l>
                           <l>"And <hi>Lycian</hi> Lots direct another way,</l>
                           <l>"To <hi>Italy.</hi> That Place muſt be above</l>
                           <l>"All Places now, that Country I muſt love.</l>
                           <l>"If you, that by your Birth <hi>Phoenician</hi> are,</l>
                           <l>"Fair <hi>Carthage</hi> Towers cou'd invite ſo far;</l>
                           <l>"How can you think it much <hi>Trojans</hi> ſhou'd try</l>
                           <l>"Their Fortune, when thus call'd, in <hi>Italy?</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"To wander alike to you and us is due;</l>
                           <l>"We may as well ſeek foreign Seats as you.</l>
                           <l>"Beſides, the great <hi>Anchiſes</hi> every Night</l>
                           <l>"Sollicites this; does eve'ry Night affright.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="107" facs="tcp:100354:61"/>"And then the Injury of my dear Son,</l>
                           <l>"The Wrong that to <hi>Aſcanius</hi> wou'd be done;</l>
                           <l>"Who muſt not loſe whatſoe'er thoſe fatal Fields,</l>
                           <l>"And what the rich <hi>Heſperian</hi> Kingdom yields.</l>
                           <l>"And now Heave'ns Meſſenger with <hi>Jove</hi>'s Com|"mand</l>
                           <l>"At laſt is come. I ſaw the' God enter, ſtand,</l>
                           <l>"Appear by day: the ſame Command he bears</l>
                           <l>"I heard it plain, I heard it with theſe Ears.</l>
                           <l>"Vex not thy ſelf with ſuch Complaints, nor me,</l>
                           <l>"I go to <hi>Italy</hi> unwillingly.</l>
                           <l>With great Averſeneſs all this while the Queen</l>
                           <l>Had heard him ſpeak, and ſhew'd it in her Meen.</l>
                           <l>Caſting about this way, and that, at firſt,</l>
                           <l>Her earneſt Eyes, at laſt enrag'd, ſhe burſt.</l>
                           <l>"No Goddeſs was thy Mother, thou 'art too baſe</l>
                           <l>"To be deſcended from the <hi>Dardan</hi> Race,</l>
                           <l>"Perſidious Man: on <hi>Caucaſus</hi> thou 'rt bred,</l>
                           <l>"And muſt have been by Milk of Tigers fed.</l>
                           <l>"Why ſhou'd I hide my Rage, and ſtill reſerve</l>
                           <l>"My ſelf to Injuries I do n't deſerve?</l>
                           <l>"Did he ſo much as ſigh to ſee me weep?</l>
                           <l>"He all this while his Countenance cou'd keep.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="108" facs="tcp:100354:62"/>"Did he ev'er offer but to ſhed a Tear?</l>
                           <l>"Or but to pity what was once ſo dear?</l>
                           <l>"O what ſhall I ſay firſt? Nor <hi>Juno</hi> can</l>
                           <l>"Nor <hi>Jupiter</hi> ev'er look upon this Man,</l>
                           <l>"With any Favour or Eſteem agen,</l>
                           <l>"<hi>There is no Faith nor Honeſty in Men.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"Caſt on my Shore, a ſhipwrack'd Man, and poor,</l>
                           <l>"I yet receiv'd, and wou'd I'd done no more.</l>
                           <l>"Mad as I was, afraid to rule alone,</l>
                           <l>"I fooliſhly too plac'd him on my Throne,</l>
                           <l>"And made my ſelf but Sharer of my own.</l>
                           <l>"I ſav'd the Remnant of his Fleet from Wrack;</l>
                           <l>"From the' Jaws of Death I brought his <hi>Trojans</hi> back.</l>
                           <l>"O, I 'am enrag'd. By <hi>Apollo</hi> he muſt tell,</l>
                           <l>"And <hi>Lycian</hi> Lots now which way to do well.</l>
                           <l>"Now <hi>Mercury</hi> from the high Heave'ns muſt come,</l>
                           <l>"And from great <hi>Jupiter</hi> to bring his Doom.</l>
                           <l>"The Gods, it ſeems, concern themſelves ſo much</l>
                           <l>"About us here. Are the' Cares of Heaven ſuch?</l>
                           <l>"I muſt confeſs, I underſtand not well</l>
                           <l>"The things you ſay, nor ever will refell.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="109" facs="tcp:100354:62"/>"Go, ſail to <hi>Italy</hi> through the wide Seas,</l>
                           <l>"Seek Kingdoms that may pleaſe you more than theſe.</l>
                           <l>"I hope the Gods (if any thing they can)</l>
                           <l>"Will <hi>ſplit</hi> upon the Rocks ſo vile a <hi>Man.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"Where, both by Gods and Men at laſt forſook,</l>
                           <l>"The Name of <hi>Dido</hi> thou ſhalt oft invoke.</l>
                           <l>"And when my Soul ſhall from theſe Limbs retire,</l>
                           <l>"I'll follow and purſue thee with dark Fire.</l>
                           <l>"When I 'am a Ghoſt, I'll eve'ry where appear,</l>
                           <l>"And thou ſhalt pay, Wretch, for thy Falſeneſs dear,</l>
                           <l>'Whilſt I below ſhall of thy Torments hear.</l>
                           <l>Whilſt thus ſhe ſpeaks, nor whilſt ſhe ſpeaks can bear</l>
                           <l>The raging Mixture of her angry Fear,</l>
                           <l>Her Life and Spirit fled: turning away</l>
                           <l>She left <hi>Aeneas</hi> thinking what to ſay,</l>
                           <l>And fainting fell.—</l>
                           <l>The ſwooning Queen the Ladies quickly led</l>
                           <l>To the' Marble-Room, and laid her on her Bod.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aeneas,</hi> though he wiſh'd her all Relief,</l>
                           <l>And fain with Words would have appeas'd her Grief,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="110" facs="tcp:100354:63"/>Though 'he deeply ſigh'd, felt all the Pangs of Love,</l>
                           <l>Yet his great Mind the Gods alone can move.</l>
                           <l>Them he obeys, his Fleet again reviews.</l>
                           <l>Again the Seamens Courage he renews.</l>
                           <l>They bring, for haſte, Oars with their Branches on,</l>
                           <l>And Oak half-wrought to work again upon.</l>
                           <l>With lofty Ships along the pleaſant Shores</l>
                           <l>They gently ſlide, and ſtoutly ply their Oars.</l>
                           <l>You ſee the <hi>Trojans</hi> now come ſwarming down</l>
                           <l>Like Troops of Ants, from all ſides of the Town.</l>
                           <l>As thoſe ſmall Creatures having in their Eye</l>
                           <l>The Cold of Winter, and its Scarcity,</l>
                           <l>The ſmall black Troop goes through the duſty Field,</l>
                           <l>Bearing through little Paths what Seaſons yield;</l>
                           <l>Some heavy loaded, ſome thruſting behind,</l>
                           <l>Some driving thoſe which they more lazy find,</l>
                           <l>Some chiding others for the leaſt delay:</l>
                           <l>So <hi>Trojans</hi> urge the Work in every way.</l>
                           <l>What thought'ſt thou, <hi>Dido,</hi> when from thy high Tower</l>
                           <l>Thou ſaw'ſt thus active all the <hi>Trojan</hi> Power?</l>
                           <l>How did'ſt thou ſigh? How was thy Sight annoy'd?</l>
                           <l>Thy Shore to view, when it was thus employ'd.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="111" facs="tcp:100354:63"/>How muſt that noiſe confus'd then needs diſpleaſe</l>
                           <l>Of flying Mariners, and roaring Seas?</l>
                           <l>But wicked Love! what doſt thou not compel</l>
                           <l>Us Mortals to?</l>
                           <l>Again ſhe's forc'd to weep, again ſhe'll try</l>
                           <l>What humble Prayers may do before ſhe dye.</l>
                           <l>Again Love ſways; and loth to dye in vain</l>
                           <l>She firſt tryes all the ways ſhe can to gain.</l>
                           <l>"Siſter, ſaid ſhe, you ſee what haſt they make,</l>
                           <l>"How faſt they ſill the ſhore; how they betake</l>
                           <l>"Them to their Ships, their Sails already ſpread</l>
                           <l>"Their Ships are Crown'd; Had I had any dread,</l>
                           <l>"Or any thoughts that he'd have left my Bed,</l>
                           <l>"This greateſt grief with which my Soul is torn,</l>
                           <l>"Foreſeen perhaps I better might have born.</l>
                           <l>"But do this one thing now, dear <hi>Anne,</hi> for me</l>
                           <l>"To ſuccour thy poor Siſter's miſery.</l>
                           <l>"This moſt perſidious Man to thee was kind,</l>
                           <l>"And us'd to make thee privy to his mind;</l>
                           <l>"You beſt the times of ſpeaking to him know.</l>
                           <l>"Go, Siſter, once more ſpeak to the proud Foe.</l>
                           <l>"I ne'er was thought, tell him, nor was of thoſe</l>
                           <l>"Who 'againſt his <hi>Troy</hi> conſpired with their Foes;</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="112" facs="tcp:100354:64"/>"Nor ſent I Ships, nor any thing t' annoy</l>
                           <l>"The glorious Empire of that ancient <hi>Troy.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"Why won't he hear at leaſt but what I ſay?</l>
                           <l>"And let me ſpeak my grief while yet I may?</l>
                           <l>"Where does he run? Let him but one thing grant,</l>
                           <l>"For all my Love, for all I am to want,</l>
                           <l>"Expect a ſmoother flight, Winds too that may</l>
                           <l>"More than theſe ſeem to do, his Gods obey.</l>
                           <l>"I do not plead, alas, a Marriage-Vow,</l>
                           <l>"Or any Promiſe he's retracting now,</l>
                           <l>"Him of fair <hi>Latium</hi> I wou'd not deceive,</l>
                           <l>"Nor wou'd I have him ſuch a Kingdom leave:</l>
                           <l>"I ask him but this pittiful relief,</l>
                           <l>"He'd give me time to mitigate my grief;</l>
                           <l>"Time but till my hard Fortune make me know,</l>
                           <l>"Since I muſt ſuffer, how t' endure my woe.</l>
                           <l>"Siſter, 'tis all I ask, do this for me:</l>
                           <l>"I will not die without rewarding thee.</l>
                           <l>Thus begg'd the grieving Queen; her Siſter goes</l>
                           <l>With as much feeling repreſents her woes.</l>
                           <l>But he's not to be mov'd with Womens tears,</l>
                           <l>Untractable, without Compaſſion hears:</l>
                           <l>The Fates oppoſe, and <hi>Jove</hi> had ſtop'd his Ears.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="113" facs="tcp:100354:64"/>Juſt as thoſe Winds which ſtriving to confound</l>
                           <l>An ancient Oak well ſetled in the ground,</l>
                           <l>Wreſting it this way 'and that, but ſtrows his leaves,</l>
                           <l>With all that noiſe and force, whilſt it ſtill cleaves</l>
                           <l>Faſt to the Rock, where its Roots as deep go</l>
                           <l>As its top's high into the Earth below.</l>
                           <l>Juſt ſo the Hero with ſuch Speeches preſt,</l>
                           <l>Though higheſt Paſſions violently wreſt</l>
                           <l>This way and that, and ſhake his lofty Breaſt;</l>
                           <l>He weeps indeed, but weeps alas, in vain:</l>
                           <l>His reſolutions ſtill unmov'd remain.</l>
                           <l>Unhappy <hi>Dido</hi> hurryed with hard Fate</l>
                           <l>To her ſad end, now grows quite deſperate.</l>
                           <l>She ſhuns the light; to ſee the glorious Sky</l>
                           <l>Is tedious to her, ſhe deſires to dye.</l>
                           <l>Wonders confirm her thoughts; for whilſt ſhe ſtands</l>
                           <l>At th' incens'd Altar, th' offering in her hands</l>
                           <l>She ſeems to ſee grow black (wonder we ſhou'd</l>
                           <l>Scarce ſpeak) the Wine turn'd into filthy blood.</l>
                           <l>This ſight the Queen diſcovered to none,</l>
                           <l>Nor wou'd unto her deareſt Siſter own.</l>
                           <l>A Marble Chapel in the Palace ſtood,</l>
                           <l>Where ſhe <hi>Sichaeus</hi> honour'd like a God:</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="114" facs="tcp:100354:65"/>Which ſhe had dreſt with Cloaths of fineſt Wool,</l>
                           <l>With Boughs and Crowns: and 'twas of Garlands full.</l>
                           <l>Here ſhe thought ſtill ſhe heard a diſmal Noiſe,</l>
                           <l>And cou'd diſtinguiſh her firſt Husband's Voice,</l>
                           <l>Calling her to him. As ſoon as 'twas Night</l>
                           <l>The fatal Screech-Owl often did affright</l>
                           <l>From the Houſe Top; Remembers then, of old,</l>
                           <l>This Fate to her by Wizards has been told:</l>
                           <l>And frights the more.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aeneas</hi> terrifies her in ſhort ſleeps,</l>
                           <l>Sleeping, ſhe ſees him leave her, dreams ſhe weeps.</l>
                           <l>Fanſies ſhe goes long Journies all alone,</l>
                           <l>And through long Deſarts ſeeking of her own</l>
                           <l>Attendants loſt.—</l>
                           <l>Juſt ſo mad <hi>Pentheus</hi> frighted ſees two Suns,</l>
                           <l>Sees double <hi>Thebes:</hi> from Troops of Furies runs.</l>
                           <l>Juſt in ſuch Caſe <hi>Oreſtes</hi> on the Stage</l>
                           <l>Frighted, amaz'd, and tortured with Rage,</l>
                           <l>From Mother arm'd with Torch and Serpents flees,</l>
                           <l>Revenging Furies watching of him ſees.</l>
                           <l>At laſt with Fury ſill'd, oppreſt with Grief,</l>
                           <l>And quite out of all Hope, of all Relief,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="115" facs="tcp:100354:65"/>Reſolves to dye, the Manner, Time, and Place,</l>
                           <l>By 'her ſelf contrives: but with a chearful Face</l>
                           <l>Diſſembling Hope, and cove'ring her Intent,</l>
                           <l>Her Siſter not ſuſpecting what ſhe meant;</l>
                           <l>Rejoice, dear <hi>Ann,</hi> ſaid ſhe, perhaps I may</l>
                           <l>Have found at leaſt a ſure and the 'only way,</l>
                           <l>Which, or will bring me to my Love again,</l>
                           <l>Or elſe, at leaſt, will eaſe me of my Pain.</l>
                           <l>By the' utmoſt Ocean, in the fartheſt Place,</l>
                           <l>That is inhabited by the' <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Race,</l>
                           <l>Where the Sun ſets, where mighty <hi>Atlas</hi> bears</l>
                           <l>Upon his Shoulders both the Stars and Sphears;</l>
                           <l>A certain Prieſteſs that came thence of late</l>
                           <l>Was brought to me, and told me all my Fate.</l>
                           <l>They ſay, ſhe's that <hi>Maſſilian</hi> born and bred,</l>
                           <l>Who the' Dragon in the' <hi>Heſperian</hi> Temple fed</l>
                           <l>With Hone'y and Poppey: that the ſacred Tree</l>
                           <l>Might by that Dragon ſo preſerved be.</l>
                           <l>This Woman ſays, ſhe can, when-ev'er ſhe pleaſe,</l>
                           <l>Afflicted Minds from any Grief releaſe.</l>
                           <l>All ſorts of Wonders ſhe is ſaid to do,</l>
                           <l>As ſhe can eaſe, ſo ſhe can torture too,</l>
                           <l>Can ſtop a River's Courſe, turn Planets back,</l>
                           <l>And from below ſhe fetches up the black</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="116" facs="tcp:100354:66"/>Nocturnal Ghoſts. —</l>
                           <l>From Mountain's Top ſhe can make Trees come down,</l>
                           <l>And the' Earth muſt groan, if ſhe ſtamp on 't and frown.</l>
                           <l>But I call God to witneſs, <hi>Anne,</hi> and thee,</l>
                           <l>I uſe ſuch Arts as theſe unwillingly.</l>
                           <l>Yet, Siſter, go, and privately erect,</l>
                           <l>In the' Inner Court, a Pile: 'tis to be deck'd</l>
                           <l>With the Spoils o' the' Impious Man; his Arms, his Clothes</l>
                           <l>That hang above, bring down, lay upon thoſe</l>
                           <l>What-ever elſe he left. Place that ſad Bed</l>
                           <l>On Top of all, in which I periſhed.</l>
                           <l>For ſo the Prieſteſs told me I muſt do,</l>
                           <l>Aboliſh with him all his Reliques too.</l>
                           <l>Here ſuddenly ſhe ſtopp'd; her Face ov'er-ſpread</l>
                           <l>With Paleneſs, look'd as if already dead.</l>
                           <l>By' her Siſter 'twas not all this while believ'd,</l>
                           <l>That <hi>Dido</hi> cou'd to ſo great Height have griev'd;</l>
                           <l>Or meant theſe Fune'ral Rites ſhou'd be her own,</l>
                           <l>Or cou'd have felt more Grief than ſhe had ſhown,</l>
                           <l>When ſhe her dear <hi>Sichaeus</hi> did bemoan.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="117" facs="tcp:100354:66"/>Therefore obey'd. A mighty Pile, and high,</l>
                           <l>Within they raiſe, and open to the Sky,</l>
                           <l>Of Oak and Pine; the Queen adorn'd it round,</l>
                           <l>Had it with Wreaths of Cypreſs-Branches crown'd.</l>
                           <l>Reſolved ſtill upon that Pile to dye,</l>
                           <l>To have <hi>Aeneas in Effigie</hi> by.</l>
                           <l>When on the Pile ſhe'd plac'd his Sword and Clothes,</l>
                           <l>She laid his Statue on the Bed, and thoſe</l>
                           <l>Several Altars 'bout this Pile of Wood</l>
                           <l>For Sacrifices new erected ſtood.</l>
                           <l>At theſe the Magick Prieſteſs, with looſe Hair,</l>
                           <l>To every God begins to make her Prayer.</l>
                           <l>Vaſt <hi>Chaos</hi> ſhe calls on, and <hi>Erebus,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Three hundred Names of Gods ſhe thunders thus.</l>
                           <l>And triple <hi>Hecate</hi>'s 'as many Names,</l>
                           <l>As ſhe has for her Vertues different Fames.</l>
                           <l>Sprinkling black Drops ſuppos'd to come from Hell,</l>
                           <l>Reſembling thoſe of the <hi>Avernal</hi> Well.</l>
                           <l>Thoſe poiſonous Magick Herbs by Moon-light ſhone,</l>
                           <l>Which with the brazen Scythe are to be mown,</l>
                           <l>The' Excreſcence on Colts Foreheads too they uſe,</l>
                           <l>And Love ſnatch'd from the Dam. —</l>
                           <l>The Queen her ſelf before the Altar ſtands,</l>
                           <l>Holding a Piece of Leaven in her Hands,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="118" facs="tcp:100354:67"/>With left Foot bare, and with the other ſhod,</l>
                           <l>Her Garments looſe, to witneſs eve'ry God</l>
                           <l>She calls; and being now to dye, beſought</l>
                           <l>All Powe'rs that cou'd be privy to her Thought,</l>
                           <l>If any 'have Care of ill-requited Love,</l>
                           <l>That they wou'd now revenge her for above.</l>
                           <l>"'Twas Night, the Time when humane Bodies take</l>
                           <l>"Their uſual Reſt, and nothing was awake.</l>
                           <l>"The Seas were quiet, and the Woods were ſtill,</l>
                           <l>"And the Night-Stars were gone down half their Hill.</l>
                           <l>"Cattel lay quiet in the ſilent Field,</l>
                           <l>"All the fine Birds, all Fiſh the Waters yield,</l>
                           <l>"All Beaſts the Foreſts feeds, all things we ſee</l>
                           <l>"In quiet Night from all their Labours free,</l>
                           <l>"Were caſing of their Care. —</l>
                           <l>But miſerable <hi>Dido</hi>'s troubled Mind</l>
                           <l>Admits no Sleep, nor any Reſt can find.</l>
                           <l>Her all this while, her diſmal Thoughts affright,</l>
                           <l>Nor does ſhe' injoy the Solaces of Night.</l>
                           <l>Her Cares increaſe, and Love renews its Toyl,</l>
                           <l>Her Breaſt begins with furious Rage to boyl.</l>
                           <l>Thus ſhe torments her ſelf. What ſhall I do?</l>
                           <l>Thoſe I ſo oft refus'd ſhall I now wooe?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="119" facs="tcp:100354:67"/>To wild <hi>Numidians,</hi> ſo oft ſcorn'd, go bow,</l>
                           <l>And court <hi>Barbarians</hi> for a Husband now?</l>
                           <l>Or leaving Kingdom, like a Captive go,</l>
                           <l>And baſely follow my inſulting Foe?</l>
                           <l>Men ſo ungrateful, when I heretofore</l>
                           <l>Befriended 'em: I'll truſt ſuch Men no more.</l>
                           <l>But though I cou'd to <hi>Trojans</hi> ſtoop ſo low,</l>
                           <l>Wou'd my own <hi>Tyrians</hi> ever let me go?</l>
                           <l>Wou'd <hi>Trojans</hi> carry me? Of all bereft?</l>
                           <l>A Perſon whom their Leader thus has left?</l>
                           <l>Ah! haſt thou not ſufficiently yet known</l>
                           <l>That falſeſt Race of baſe <hi>Laomedon?</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>What ſhall I do then? Fly with ſuch as theſe</l>
                           <l>Triumphing Foes, alone through the vaſt Seas?</l>
                           <l>Or elſe my old <hi>Sidonians</hi> again,</l>
                           <l>Which I from home brought hither with ſuch Pain,</l>
                           <l>Draw forth? Purſue? —</l>
                           <l>No, rather dye than hope for ſuch Relief,</l>
                           <l>Thou haſt deſerv'd it, let Steel end thy Grief.</l>
                           <l>Ah! Siſter, you betray'd me to all this,</l>
                           <l>Mov'd by my Tears help'd me to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o amiſs.</l>
                           <l>Mad that I was, I might have ſtill been free</l>
                           <l>As the poor dulleſt Brutes by Nature be;</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="120" facs="tcp:100354:68"/>And then I had been ſtill until this time,</l>
                           <l>Without my Trouble, and without my Crime.</l>
                           <l>But Oh, I broke the Vow which I had made,</l>
                           <l>My dear <hi>Sichaeus,</hi> to thy ſacred Shade.</l>
                           <l>With ſuch Complaints as theſe tortu'ring her Breſt</l>
                           <l>Continually, ſhe never was at reſt.</l>
                           <l>Mean while <hi>Aeneas,</hi> while the Queen thus weeps,</l>
                           <l>Shipt, and reſolv'd to go, ſecurely ſleeps;</l>
                           <l>When once again a God from Heave'n was ſeen</l>
                           <l>By him aſleep, in Shape he had been in</l>
                           <l>Not long before. —</l>
                           <l>He came like <hi>Mercury;</hi> his Colour, Hair,</l>
                           <l>His Voice and Limbs had a <hi>Mercurial</hi> Air;</l>
                           <l>Who ſpake to' him thus; "And canſt thou, Goddeſs Son,</l>
                           <l>"So ſoundly ſleep when ſo near be'ing undone?</l>
                           <l>"Art thou ſo fooliſh, as not yet to ſee</l>
                           <l>"In how great danger thou muſt quickly be?</l>
                           <l>"Do you not hear how fair a Wind you have?</l>
                           <l>"What have you more then of the Gods to crave?</l>
                           <l>"She 's plotting Miſchief, what Crime wo' n't ſhe try,</l>
                           <l>"What wo' n't ſhe do, who is reſolv'd to dye?</l>
                           <l>"Wo'n't you be gone whilſt yet you ſafely may?</l>
                           <l>"If till to morrow Morning you delay,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="121" facs="tcp:100354:68"/>"The Sea all cover'd with her Ships you'll ſee,</l>
                           <l>"And this Shore flame with Fire to ruine thee.</l>
                           <l>"O flee, or to your Sorrow you will find</l>
                           <l>"<hi>Nothing ſo' inconſtant as a Woman's Mind.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Having thus ſpoke, he mingled with the Night;</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Aeneas</hi> at the Viſion in a Fright,</l>
                           <l>Starts from his ſleep, prepares his Men for Flight.</l>
                           <l>Make haſte, ſaid he, all to your Places, Row,</l>
                           <l>Hoiſe all your Sails, Gods from above do ſhow</l>
                           <l>We muſt cut Cables, and with ſpeed be gone,</l>
                           <l>This is the Second Time we 'are call'd upon.</l>
                           <l>We come, O ſacred God, we follow thee,</l>
                           <l>We chearfully obey who ev'er thou be.</l>
                           <l>O be propitious to the <hi>Trojan</hi> ſide,</l>
                           <l>And through all Dangers be thou ſtill our Guide.</l>
                           <l>With that he drew, ſoon as he'd ſpoke the Word,</l>
                           <l>And cut the Cable with his glittering Sword.</l>
                           <l>The luſty <hi>Trojans</hi> all with one accord,</l>
                           <l>Fall to their Work, quickly put off from Shore,</l>
                           <l>The Sea with their tall Ships is cover'd o're,</l>
                           <l>They cleave the Deep, and make the Ocean roar.</l>
                           <l>But now <hi>Aurore</hi> leaving her Scarlet Bed,</l>
                           <l>New Light began upon the Earth to ſpread.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="122" facs="tcp:100354:69"/>'Soon as the Queen perceived it was day,</l>
                           <l>Saw from her Towers the <hi>Trojans</hi> on their way,</l>
                           <l>Under full Sail: And when ſhe ſaw no more</l>
                           <l>Of <hi>Trojan</hi> Fleet left on the <hi>Tyrian</hi> Shore;</l>
                           <l>Then ſhe began to beat her comely Breſt,</l>
                           <l>Tearing her Hair, Thus ſhe her Grief expreſt.</l>
                           <l>"And ſhall this Stranger, <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſaid ſhe,</l>
                           <l>"Delude thus baſely both my Realms and me?</l>
                           <l>"Sha' n't I purſue with Arms? With all the Town?</l>
                           <l>"With all my Ships? O let 'em all fall down.</l>
                           <l>"Go, bid 'em haſten, let 'em row apace,</l>
                           <l>"Carry Fire quickly, burn 'em in the Place.</l>
                           <l>"But where am I? What do I ſay? I 'am mad,</l>
                           <l>"Unhappy <hi>Dido,</hi> now thy Fortune 's bad.</l>
                           <l>"Then you ſhou'd have purſu'd, when firſt he came.</l>
                           <l>"When you gave Sceptres, when you loſt your Fame,</l>
                           <l>"Is this his Faith? And is this all the Odds</l>
                           <l>"'Twixt other Men, and him that carries Gods</l>
                           <l>"About with him? —</l>
                           <l>"Is this he, who whilſt Foes <hi>Troy</hi> burn and ſack,</l>
                           <l>"Brought his old Father out upon his Back?</l>
                           <l>"Why cou'd not I that Body' of his have tore,</l>
                           <l>"And thrown his ſcatter'd Limbs about the Shore?</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="123" facs="tcp:100354:69"/>"Have ſlain his <hi>Trojans?</hi> Why did I not cut</l>
                           <l>"The Son in pieces, and the Father glut</l>
                           <l>"With the Boy dreſt? I ſhou'd have made him eat,</l>
                           <l>"His darling Son inſtead of dainty Meat.</l>
                           <l>"But the' Fight, perhaps, wou'd have been doubtful then;</l>
                           <l>"I that will dye, what ſhou'd I fear from Men?</l>
                           <l>"I ſhou'd have burnt the Fleet, and all on ſire,</l>
                           <l>"My cruel Rage ſhou'd have gone one ſtep higher.</l>
                           <l>"I ſhou'd have ſlain together Fathe'r and Son,</l>
                           <l>"Have thrown my ſelf among 'em when I'd done.</l>
                           <l>"But you, O <hi>Phoebus,</hi> that with glorious Light</l>
                           <l>"Vieweſt the Earth, of all things haſt a ſight;</l>
                           <l>"You, <hi>Juno,</hi> privy to the Lover's Care,</l>
                           <l>"Judge of all Injuries that Spouſes bear;</l>
                           <l>"Nocturnal <hi>Hecate',</hi> I invoke you all,</l>
                           <l>"Ye Furies too, revenge <hi>Eliza</hi>'s Fall.</l>
                           <l>"Receive theſe Praye'rs of mine, apply your Power</l>
                           <l>"To do me Juſtice, in this fatal Hour.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>"If this abominable Man muſt gain</l>
                           <l>"The Hav'en he ſeeks; and if <hi>Jove</hi> ſo ordain,</l>
                           <l>"Yet there let him be curs'd, be vex'd with Arms</l>
                           <l>"Of a bold Nation, and with all the Harms</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="124" facs="tcp:100354:70"/>"That War can bring. Let his <hi>Iulus</hi> be</l>
                           <l>"Torn from him; baniſhed in Miſery.</l>
                           <l>"Let him behold the lamentable Ends</l>
                           <l>"Of all his dear, and beſt deſerving Friends.</l>
                           <l>"Let him beg help, and be deny'd; ſubmit</l>
                           <l>"On baſe Conditions to what is not fit:</l>
                           <l>"And when he ſhall have ended thus his Strife,</l>
                           <l>"Let him enjoy neither his Throne, nor Life:</l>
                           <l>"But long before his Time unhappy dye,</l>
                           <l>"And on ſome Shore let him unburied lye.</l>
                           <l>"This, Gods, I beg; let me be underſtood,</l>
                           <l>"This my laſt Prayer I pour forth with my Blood.</l>
                           <l>"But you, O <hi>Tyrians,</hi> with that curſed Race</l>
                           <l>"Of <hi>Trojans,</hi> Friendſhip never more embrace.</l>
                           <l>"Hate ſtill that Nation mortally you muſt,</l>
                           <l>"And with that Enmity oblige our Duſt.</l>
                           <l>"'Twixt them and us, O, never let there be</l>
                           <l>"Or League, or any kind of Amity.</l>
                           <l>"May from our Bones ſome fierce Revenger riſe,</l>
                           <l>"With Fire and Sword to' inveſt their Colonies.</l>
                           <l>"And whenſoev'er it be, when we in length</l>
                           <l>"Of Time, hereafter ſhall have gotten ſtrength,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="125" facs="tcp:100354:70"/>"Our Shores, their Shores; our Fleets their Fleets oppoſe,</l>
                           <l>"And let our Sons be born each other's Foes.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>This ſaid, the Queen with Anguiſh look'd about,</l>
                           <l>As if her Soul had ſtrugled to get out,</l>
                           <l>Thinking which way ſhe now might get from light,</l>
                           <l>She hated ſo, and from all mortal ſight;</l>
                           <l>She ſpoke to 'her Husbands Nurſe, her own was dead,</l>
                           <l>(<hi>Barce</hi> they call'd her) thus ſhe briefly ſaid:</l>
                           <l>"Go, deareſt Nurſe, with all the haſt you can,</l>
                           <l>"Fetch hither preſently my Siſter <hi>Anne.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"Go bid her ſprinkle 'her ſelf and come away,</l>
                           <l>"And bring the Sheep and Victims I'm to pay;</l>
                           <l>"And you, pray dreſs your ſelf in ſuch a Veil</l>
                           <l>"As fits this Service, in which we bewail</l>
                           <l>"My loſs—</l>
                           <l>"I mean to ſacrifice to <hi>Stygian Jove,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>"As I've deſign'd, ſo put an end to Love;</l>
                           <l>"Burn the <hi>Dardanian</hi> where his Reliques lye,</l>
                           <l>"Here <hi>in Effigie</hi> that my love may dye.</l>
                           <l>So ſpake the Queen, but the good Nurſe did go</l>
                           <l>Creeping and ſlowly as old Women do.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="126" facs="tcp:100354:71"/>
                              <hi>Dido</hi> mean while enflam'd with wild deſire,</l>
                           <l>And with mad thoughts, her Face was all on ſire.</l>
                           <l>Her colour came and went, reſolv'd to dye,</l>
                           <l>Pale with the thought, does in a Fury fly</l>
                           <l>Up the high Pile. —</l>
                           <l>That fatal gift for no ſuch uſe bequeath'd,</l>
                           <l>The <hi>Trojan</hi>'s Sword there preſently unſheath'd:</l>
                           <l>Then caſting of her Eyes upon his Cloths,</l>
                           <l>And that known Bed; where they us'd to repoſe,</l>
                           <l>Pauſing a while, cou'd not ev'en then forbear</l>
                           <l>To ſacriſice to thoſe dear ſpoils a Tear.</l>
                           <l>Throwing her ſelf on the beloved Bed,</l>
                           <l>Kiſſing the Garments, theſe laſt words ſhe ſaid:</l>
                           <l>"Dear Reliques of my Love, whilſt Fate thought ſit,</l>
                           <l>"And whilſt the Gods were pleas'd to ſuffer it,</l>
                           <l>"Let me here eaſe all Cares of what is paſt;</l>
                           <l>"Hore upon you breath forth my Soul at laſt.</l>
                           <l>"I've liv'd, finiſht that courſe that Fortune gave;</l>
                           <l>"I ſhall go great enough into my Grave.</l>
                           <l>"My Husband I've reveng'd, and of my Foe</l>
                           <l>"My Brother, I have had juſt Vengeance too.</l>
                           <l>"I've built my City, I have rais'd a Wall,</l>
                           <l>"That is in no great likelyhood to fall.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="127" facs="tcp:100354:71"/>"Happy, thrice happy, I might ſtill have been,</l>
                           <l>"If <hi>Trojans</hi> never had my Kingdom ſeen.</l>
                           <l>Theſe words when the unfortunate had ſaid,</l>
                           <l>Then groveling with her Face upon the Bed,</l>
                           <l>"But muſt we dye too unreveng'd? ſaid ſhe,</l>
                           <l>"Yet let us dye, thus to the ſhades we'll flee.</l>
                           <l>"'Tis in this manner we delight to go,</l>
                           <l>"Thus, thus, we'll paſs unto the Gods below.</l>
                           <l>"And let the cruel <hi>Trojan</hi> from the deep</l>
                           <l>"Behold this Funeral of mine, and weep.</l>
                           <l>"And let him too as long as he hath breath</l>
                           <l>"Bear with him theſe ill Omens of my Death.</l>
                           <l>'Soon as ſhe'd ſpoke, the Attendants ſaw her fall,</l>
                           <l>With the Sword thruſt quite through her, reeking all</l>
                           <l>With her warm Blood: ſhe fell with her Arms ſpread,</l>
                           <l>And thus ſhe lay upon the fatal Bed.</l>
                           <l>'Soon as they'd ſeen her fall, there went a cry</l>
                           <l>Through Palace, Town, as 'if all had been to dye.</l>
                           <l>The news ſo diſmal was, all <hi>Carthage</hi> ſhook</l>
                           <l>As 'if Foes had entred, <hi>Carthage</hi> had been took.</l>
                           <l>Or juſt as if at taking of old <hi>Tyre,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>The Town and Temples too had been on ſire.</l>
                           <l>Her Siſter heard it, half dead with the fright,</l>
                           <l>Breaks through the tumult (a moſt doleful ſight.)</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="128" facs="tcp:100354:72"/>Beating her Breaſt, and tearing of her Face,</l>
                           <l>Gets quite at laſt unto the diſmal place.</l>
                           <l>She calls her dying Siſter by her name,</l>
                           <l>"Is it for this, Siſter, ſaid ſhe, I came?</l>
                           <l>"Was it to get an opportunity</l>
                           <l>"You ſent your Nurſe ſo falſly then to me?</l>
                           <l>"Nought elſe, it ſeems, theſe Altars, Piles and Fires</l>
                           <l>"Were to obtain, but this worſt of deſires.</l>
                           <l>"What ſhall I firſt complain of? That I'm left?</l>
                           <l>"Or that I'm loſt, or that I am bereft</l>
                           <l>"Of you, dear Siſter? Why did you not make</l>
                           <l>"Me now Companion? Why don't I partake</l>
                           <l>"In this Fate too? Why was't not in my power</l>
                           <l>"By the ſame Sword to die too the ſame hour?</l>
                           <l>"Did I with my own hands this Pile erect?</l>
                           <l>"Did I invoke the Gods to this effect?</l>
                           <l>"That I might now be abſent at the laſt,</l>
                           <l>"And not ſuſpect the miſchief till 'twas paſt?</l>
                           <l>"I've ſlain you, Siſter, and my ſelf withall:</l>
                           <l>"Our Peers, our People: I've been all your fall.</l>
                           <l>"O let me waſh your Wound, Siſter, your breath,</l>
                           <l>"If any 's left, receive too at your Death.</l>
                           <l>With ſuch like words as theſe grieving, ſhe paſt</l>
                           <l>The high Piles ſtairs, and being got up at laſt,</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="129" facs="tcp:100354:72"/>Her dying Siſter, on her Arms ſhe reſts,</l>
                           <l>And ſighing dryes her blood up with her Veſt.</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Dido</hi> mean while, to open ſtrives, in vain</l>
                           <l>Her heavy Eyes; ſtill ſwoons away again.</l>
                           <l>Thrice ſhe lifts up her ſelf, ſome little ſtay</l>
                           <l>Her Elbow gives, thrice again ſwoons away;</l>
                           <l>Seeks with her wandring Eyes bright Heaven's light,</l>
                           <l>Sighs when ſhe finds it at th' ungrateful ſight;</l>
                           <l>But powerful <hi>Juno</hi> pitying her long grief,</l>
                           <l>And too hard pangs, ſent <hi>Iris</hi> t' her relief,</l>
                           <l>To looſe thoſe Bands of Life 'twixt Body and Soul,</l>
                           <l>From ſo great miſery to eaſe the whole.</l>
                           <l>For ſince ſhe fell by no juſt Laws of Fate,</l>
                           <l>But furious, did her Death anticipate,</l>
                           <l>Nor did deſerve to die for any Crime,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Proſerpina</hi> cou'd not before her time</l>
                           <l>Cut off her yellow Hair; nor cou'd condemn</l>
                           <l>Her Soul ſo haſtily to be with them.</l>
                           <l>And therefore <hi>Iris</hi> with her ruddy Wings</l>
                           <l>All Colours which an adverſe Sunſhine brings,</l>
                           <l>Flies down, and ſtanding on the dying head;</l>
                           <l>"This fatal Lock, as I am bid, ſhe ſaid,</l>
                           <l>"I bear to <hi>Dis,</hi> and ſo I ſet thee free,</l>
                           <l>"Confined Soul, from all thy miſery</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="130" facs="tcp:100354:73"/>This ſaid, ſhe cut, with her right hand, her Hair,</l>
                           <l>And preſently the Soul went into Air.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Metell.</speaker>
               <l>We heard as if we all concern'd had been</l>
               <l>In the ſad Fate of the <hi>Deſerted Queen.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But he had done, and hardly we forbear</l>
               <l>To ſhed with great St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> here a tear.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Curio</hi> upbraided, thought no love could be</l>
               <l>Heroick Love without Fidelity.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acer</hi> thought Love whereever it was ſeen,</l>
               <l>With falſeneſs cou'd have little of Love's meen.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laelius</hi> on <hi>Dido</hi> as on Spouſe did look:</l>
               <l>Wondred ſhe cou'd by a 'Hero be forſook.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeſculape</hi> thought of Hero 'twas ill done,</l>
               <l>To leave a Queen, nay Miſtreſs, when once won.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Metell</hi> that long had honour'd <hi>Virgill</hi>'s Wit,</l>
               <l>Thus much thought fit to ſay 'in defence of it.</l>
               <l>"We all to Heav'n owe all: a call from thence</l>
               <l>"To higher Love, might with a leſs diſpenſe.</l>
               <l>"The greateſt Hero, and bravely enough, might leave</l>
               <l>"Miſtreſs at ſuch a Call, and not deceive.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Curio</hi> ſaid, he much deſir'd to ſhow</l>
               <l>How much worſe now, without Call, Chriſtians do</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:100354:73"/>Thou ſhalt next meeting have thy juſt deſire,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Metellus</hi> ſaid. We 'have matter will require</l>
               <l>Thy curious pains. —</l>
               <l>We all were ſtartled, and began to muſe</l>
               <l>What matter 'twas the learn'd <hi>Metell</hi> wou'd chooſe</l>
               <l>When <hi>Acer</hi> ſaid. Let's boldly attack the Age,</l>
               <l>And with the times diſpute <hi>Concubinage.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Strike not at Perſons, ſaid <hi>Metellus,</hi> then,</l>
               <l>Only at Vice, for we our ſelves are Men.</l>
               <l>And if thou doſt, and exce'llent well, but that;</l>
               <l>That is enough yet to be hooted at.</l>
               <l>'Tis true, ſaid <hi>Acer, Curio</hi> yet and I</l>
               <l>Learn'd <hi>Aeſculape</hi> and <hi>Laelius</hi> both defie</l>
               <l>In this great Cauſe, if but <hi>Metell</hi> be by.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Metell.</speaker>
               <l>Scorn <hi>Cenſures</hi> then: by Mortals be not aw'd:</l>
               <l>More than <hi>Metell,</hi> all Heaven will applaud.</l>
               <l>But you muſt here ſubmit to hardeſt Fate,</l>
               <l>Such as belongs to Vertue's Advocate.</l>
               <l>You, <hi>Laelius,</hi> and, you, <hi>Aeſculape,</hi> ſhall be,</l>
               <l>Th' plauſible Advocates of Liberty.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Metellus</hi> roſe, and we all went away,</l>
               <l>Reſolv'd to meet on the appointed day.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
